[Piano Keys Struck Once]
[Piano]
霍兰先生的乐章
[Piano Continues]
校译：zyliupost
[Strings Join In]
[Orchestra Joins In]
[Orchestra Continues]
“今日早间新闻 高华德参议员正在科罗拉多州竞选”
[Man On Radio] At the top of the news this morning...
“距肯尼迪总统遇刺快一年”
Senator Barry Goldwater is campaigning in Colorado today.
“华伦委员会称即将揭开真相...”
The Warren Commission, almost a full year after the Kennedy assassination...
-格伦,起床 -不,再睡一会儿
said that it's close to releasing...
起来,再赖床我就剪断你的钢琴弦了
- Glenn, it's time. - No, no, just a little more.
Come on, if you don't get up right now, I'm gonna cut one of your piano strings.
-几点了? -差一刻钟七点
Oh. Oh. What time is it?
差一刻钟七点!
- Quarter to 7:00. - A quarter to 7:00.
天啊
太阳这么早就升起来了?
- Mm-hmm. - Oh, God.
我也很吃惊,我还拍了照片呢 怕以后再也看不到了
Does the sun really come out this early?
It was a surprise to me too. I took a picture of it in case it never happens again.
-没人这么早起床的 -当然有
Nobody gets up this early.
起床!求你了
Oh, yes, they do.
-快起床!快起床! -不!傻瓜才起早呢
- Come on, come on, come on. Please, please, please. - No, no, no.
- No, no, no, no, no. This is a stupid idea. - Come on, come on, come on.
艾丽丝 这差事绝对不适合我
Oh! Oh, this is definitely not my scene, Iris.
先试试看,要真是不行，再找别的工作
It's just a gig. If it doesn't work, you can try something else.
-我应该几点到? -七点半
七点半?
- What time am I supposed to be there? - 7:30.
哪有人早上七点半上班的?
7:30?
What kind of people like to go to work at 7:30 in the morning?
1964年秋
[Music]
“约翰?F?肯尼迪高中”
"One, two, three"
"Oh, that's how elementary"
# One, two, three #
"It's gonna be"
# Oh, that's how elementary #
"Come on Let's fall in love"
# It's gonna be #
"It's easy (It's so easy)"
# Come on Let's fall in love #
"Like takin' candy from a baby"
# It's easy # # It's so easy #
# Like takin' candy from a baby #
"A , B, C"
# A, B, C # # A, B, C #
"Fallin' in love with you was"
"Easy for me"
# Fallin' in love with you was #
"And you can do it too"
# Easy for me # # Easy for me #
"It's easy (It's so easy)"
# And you can do it too #
"Like takin' candy from a baby"
# It's easy # # It's so easy #
嗨!
# Like takin' candy from a baby #
我是格伦?霍兰,新来的音乐老师
Hi!
我是副校长--华德斯
I'm Glenn Holland. I'm the new music teacher.
老天!
Vice Principal Wolters.
Holy cow.
-科威尔型?  -是的
拉尔夫·纳德曾著书说这型车不安全
- Corvair. - Yeah.
除非他送我部新车...否则我只能将它开到散架为止
I take it you didn't read Ralph Nader's book.
Well, unless Ralph is willing to buy me a new car...
相信你不用等太久
I think I'm gonna have to stick with this one until the wheels fall off.
Well, you may not have to wait that long. [Chuckles]
-祝你一切顺利 -谢谢
- Have a nice day. - Thanks.
"It's easy (It's so easy)"
# It's easy # # It's so easy #
"Like takin' candy from a baby"
# Like takin' candy from a baby. #
你好像迷路了,霍兰先生
我是海伦·雅各布斯,记得吗?聘你的人
You look lost, Mr. Holland.
噢!
Helen Jacobs, remember? I hired you.
是的,真抱歉.我不是迷路,只是在找…
Oh! Of course you did. I'm sorry.
No, no, I'm not... It was not that I'm lost.
-没错,我迷路了 -真是好兆头
I was just looking for the... Well, yes, of course I'm lost.
这边来吧
What an auspicious beginning.
第一天当老师,激动吗?
This way.
是紧张,从没想过会当老师
Your first day as a teacher, Mr. Holland. Excited?
没想过,为什么?
[Sighs] Nervous. Boy, I never thought I'd be here.
嗯,和大多数人一样 我考取教育学位...只是为留条退路
No? Why not?
现在果然派上用场
Well, like most people, I only got my teaching certificate...
克拉里奇先生，这里不是露天影院,手放开
so I'd have something to fall back on.
- And now I have. - This isn't a drive in, Mr. Claridge. Hands off.
霍兰先生,我不认为 从事教育工作是"退路"
You know, Mr. Holland, I don't think of teaching as a "fall-back" position.
- 不,不,我不是那意思 - 这种想法一直令我不安
我很高兴能来教书,真的
- No, I didn't mean it that way. - I grow nervous around people who do.
好,待会到我办公室来 我有份辅导学生名单给你
- I'm really very happy to be here. Really. - Good.
You'll drop by my office later on. I have a list of students you'll be advising.
辅导?请问安排在什么时间?
"Advising"? Can I ask when I'm supposed to be doing this advising?
时间由你和学生约定,你几时跟乐队见面?
That's for you and the student to arrange.
第五节课
- You meet your orchestra when? - Fifth period.
-乐队怎么样? -他们一直很努力
顺便说一下 周五前把完整的教学计划给我
- Are they any good? - They try hard.
And by the way, I'll need a complete lesson plan from you by Friday.
-好的 -九月和十月份的进度
好
Right.
- For September and October. - Right.
[Students Chattering]
[Sighing]
[Door Opens]
[Chattering]
[Bell Rings]
“霍兰先生”
好了大家 快找个座位坐好
[Boy] Let's go sit up in the back.
All right, people, come on, let's, uh...
快一点 不要耽误时间
Let's take our seats a little quicker, please. A little quicker. We're losing time.
我是霍兰先生
Come on in, come on in. Take...
当然这是礼节性的称呼
My name is Mr. Holland. This, of course, is a title of courtesy.
相应地，只要条件允许 我也会称你们为"先生"或"小姐"
And I will extend back to you...
uh, Mister or Miss as the circumstances allow.
欢迎参加《音乐欣赏》课
这门课我们将学习...音乐史
Uh, welcome to Music Appreciation.
This is a class in which we will be studying the...
谁能告诉我音乐是什么?
the history of music.
Um, who would like to give me a definition of what music is?
任何音乐?怎么样?
Any music. What do you think?
音乐的概念是什么?大致定义是什么?
Music. What do they think that music is in general?
有谁知道?
What do they think? Anybody?
没人知道?
好吧,我们来看课本…
Nobody?
Okay, let's, uh, let's go to the text.
翻到…第四页…
And we turn to page...
这儿写着："音乐是一种声音..." "由旋律及和声组成..."
um, four.
And we read that music is...
"sound in melodic or harmonic combinations...
"由人声或乐器发出"
whether produced by voice or instrument. "
现在,有问题吗?
都没有…问题吗?
Now, questions?
Anybody... at all?
没有吗?
嗯?
No? Hmm? Good.
好
现在
请大家都放松
All righty, uh, now, I just...
You know, I just want you all to relax.
就当随便玩玩 不熟练也没关系
Have a little fun. You know, we're not here to impress each other.
好了,请准备
[Chuckles] Okay. All right, let's get ready.
所有人,准备
Everyone. Come on.
可以了吗?
You ready?
好,开始
Okay, here we go.
（贝多芬第五交响曲,即"命运交响曲"）
[Beethoven: "Fifth Symphony"]
[Dissonant]
[Playing Stops]
还不错
艾伦森小姐,请起立
It was good.
Miss Aronson. Ma'am... Would you stand up, please? Stand up, please.
请起立
裙子长度符合规定吗?跪下,两个都跪,快!
Is that skirt regulation length? - Yes.
果然违规,跟我去见校长 我们要通知家长
- On your knees, both of you, right now. - I just got this dress.
I thought so. Come with me. You're coming to the principal's office.
你们回家换过合格的裙子再来
We're calling your parents, and you are going home.
- 华老师,这不公平 -我很公正
- You can come back when you're dressed properly. - Oh, Mr. Wolters.
如果放过你们便会人人效仿
- But you're not being fair. - I am being fair.
-你好 -你好
If I allow you to do it, everyone is allowed to do it.
- Hi. - Hi.
让开,别挡路
Come on. Out of my way.
-教师不用排队 -你说什么?
高中不讲民主,老师不用排队
- Teachers don't wait. - Pardon me?
High school is not a democracy.
比尔?梅斯特,体育老师
Teachers don't wait. Bill Meister, phys. Ed.
格伦?霍兰,音乐老师
- Glenn Holland. Music teacher. - Hi.
-给你 -老天
-这是什么? -星期一的菜色,罐头火鸡
There you go.
Oh, my God, what is this?
可以当灰泥砌墙
It's Monday. It's turkey Spam surprise.
一点忠告,午餐一定要自备
You could mortar walls with it.
-你带的呢? -第二课时就吃光了
Word of advice. Always bring a bag lunch.
别取笑我!我需要进补
- Where's yours? - I ate it in second period.
过去10年你在做些什么?
Sylvie, don't tease me. I need extra.
音乐巡演
[Meister] So what have you been doin' for the last ten years?
- 夜总会,婚礼,犹太成人典礼，诸如此类的 - 等等
I've been playin' music. Been on the road.
You know, um, clubs and weddings and bar mitzvahs.
我敢说你在那些会所酒吧 一定艳福不浅吧?
- That sort of thing. - Wait a minute.
夜总会美女如云你不要 却跑来这当老师?
I bet you met a ton of chicks in those clubs, huh?
So you're in these clubs, there are all these women there...
我教书是为了…
why'd you become a teacher?
Oh, actually I started teaching because...
希望有空闲作曲,其实我是作曲家
I was hoping it would give me some free time to do some composing.
I'm a composer. That's what I really do.
-有什么好笑的? -教书有空闲?
What? What's so funny?
霍兰,我都不记得我什么时候有过空闲
Oh, the free time.
Glenn, I can't remember the last time I had that was free.
[Children Chattering]
我都计划好了
你的薪水加上我摄影赚的钱
[Iris] I've got it all figured out.
再过四年,你就可以辞职
With your salary, plus what I take in with the photography...
专心作曲,来个名利双收
in four years we should have enough for you to quit...
and do nothing but compose music and become famous and make us rich.
-我撑不了四年 -我今天赚了32元
I'll never make it.
了不起 今天我可是让32个孩子 在课堂上昏昏欲睡
- I made us $32 today. - Big deal.
哦,对了.就是这儿!
I made 32 kids sleep with their eyes open. Ow!
就是这里
Right there. Right... Yeah.
Right there. Yeah.
艾莉丝,这差事比我想象的还难
[Sighs, Chuckles]
Iris,
I think this is gonna be a lot rougher gig than I originally thought.
我上高中时…常常想逃课
[Sighs]
You know, when I was in high school, I wanted to be someplace else, you know.
只要不呆在学校就好
从来不知道我的老师们也会与我有同感
Anyplace. It never occurred to me that my teachers would feel the same way.
你现在就可以辞职
-不.我们说好的 -留在乐团也不错
Well, you can still quit.
Naw, we've been through all that.
是啊,余生都呆在假日酒店表演
I thought the band was getting pretty good actually.
-要不然去洛杉矶 -我不想做呆在录音棚里的音乐家
Yeah, yeah, we could play Holiday Inns for the rest of our lives.
- Or Los Angeles. - I don't want to be a studio musician.
那就再教四年书
So, it's four years teaching then.
过来
Come here.
你上高中时…
你有没有想过你的老师们 回家像我们这样?
When you were in high school...
我的高中老师都是牧师和修女
did you ever wonder if your teachers went home and got it on at night?
When I was in high school, my teachers were all priests and nuns.
高中时我曾迷恋格里菲思先生 随时都愿意让他领回家
I had such a crush on Mr. Griffith.
真的吗?
- He could have taken me home anytime. - Really?
格里菲思先生是谁?
- Mm-hmm. - And who was this Mr. Griffith?
我的音乐老师
Oh, he was my music teacher.
[Both Laughing]
[Woodwinds: Dissonant]
好了,停
[Note Cracks]
不错,真的不错
- Okay, okay, that wasn't bad. - [Playing Stops]
-抱歉…你叫?  -蓝格
That wasn't bad at all. Um, Miss... I'm sorry.
-什么? -格特鲁德?蓝格
- Lang. - Pardon me?
好,蓝格小姐.可否由第37小节吹起?
- Lang, Gertrude Lang. - Okay, Miss Lang.
Um, would you take it from bar 37, please?
[Shakily]
[Note Cracks]
好了,好了
[Students Snickering]
很好
Okay, okay, good.
今天到此为止,明天见,干得好!
- [Bell Rings] - Good, um... That's enough for today.
蓝格小姐,你留下来好吗?
I'll see you all tomorrow. Very good work.
Miss Lang?
Would you mind hanging for a moment, please?
你的高低音转换有问题
You seem to be having a little trouble getting through the break.
我知道
-你玩这乐器多久了? -3年
I know.
- How long have you been playing? - Three years.
真的吗?
Really?
你平常有足够时间练习吗?
Uh... [Chuckles]
And do you find that you get all the practice time that you need?
一直没有间断过
I practice constantly. Yeah.
那么…
[Sighs]
我想我们…得花点时间做个别辅导
Well, then I think... I think maybe...
you and I should find some time to work on an individual basis.
-好极了 -我没有太多时间
没关系,学一点是一点  我非常非常想吹好
- That would be great. - I-I don't have a lot of time.
That's okay. Doesn't matter. Whatever you can give me.
我相信你能行
That would be wonderful. I really, really, really want to do good at this.
不如明早提前半小时到校 我们就可以开始
I bet you do. Um, well, why don't you...
come in about a half hour before first period tomorrow and we'll just start?
好的,谢谢你....非常非常感谢
Okay. All r... Thank you, thank you very much. Thanks.
[Door Opens]
当音符前有这样的降调符号时
When a flat precedes a note like this...
表示演奏时要降低半个音
it indicates that the note is to be played a half step lower.
F大调的曲子
五线谱每行的前端都会有一个这样的符号
A piece based in the F major scale should have a flat sign...
at the beginning of every stave.
“考试成绩：F”
这次考试成绩…一塌糊涂
These tests are pathetic.
“说出一位美国作曲家.”
史威林小姐,你竟回答…?
"Name an American composer. "
“巴赫”?
- Miss Swedlin, your answer was? - Bach?
"约翰?塞巴斯蒂安?巴赫"(德国)
- [Student Giggles] - Johann Sebastian Bach.
这个答卷就更有意思
Oh, this... This is my favorite one.
“如何知道某个协奏曲是什么调式?”
"How do you know what key a concerto is in?"
米姆先生,你的答案是:“翻看乐谱第一页?”
Mr. Mims, your answer was:
"Look on the front page?"
这问号表示你不确定?
Now, this question mark. Was that because...
还是说你的英文和乐理一样差劲?
you weren't sure or because your English skills...
这些测验简直是浪费你我的时间!
are on the same level as your musical theory?
说真的!我宁可去干点别的
These tests are a waste of my time and yours.
沙利文先生!去向华校长报到!
No kidding. I'd rather be somewhere else.
Mr. Sullivan, why don't you pay a visit to Mr. Wolters?
马上收拾好你的书,滚出去!
Right now! Get your books and get outta here!
其余的人拿出课本
As for the rest of you, get your textbooks out.
我们一题题找答案,直到弄懂为止
We're gonna go over these answers one by one until you get them right.
[Bell Rings]
[Boy] Aaron, wait up.
[Chattering, Laughing]
[Clarinet]
[Note Cracks]
格兰小姐 停止吧（有"放弃"的歧义）
Give it up, Miss Lang.
[Crying]
[Crying Continues]
我是说今天别吹了
-我是说放学了 -我明白你的意思
I meant for the day.
那么...为什么哭?
School's out, Miss Lang. I-I meant give it up for the day.
我太差劲了,霍兰先生
- I know what you meant. - Then?
- Why are you crying? - I'm terrible. I'm...
-嘴唇都吹肿了 -学乐器是要下苦功的
I'm terrible, Mr. Holland. I practice 'til my lips swell up.
可我吹出来的只是噪音
- Miss Lang, it takes a lot of work... - All I make is noise.
我只想有项专长
To learn a musical instrument.
我姐姐凭芭蕾奖学金上了朱丽亚音乐学院
I just want to be good at something.
My sister's got a ballet scholarship to go to Juilliard.
我哥哥得了圣母大学的橄榄球奖学金
And my brother's going to Notre Dame on a football scholarship.
我妈妈的水彩画多次获州冠军...
My mother's won the blue ribbon for watercolors at the state fair so many times...
以致主办方不得不停办这项比赛
我父亲有副天生的好嗓子
they've retired the category.
My father's got the most beautiful voice. He's...
我是全家唯一没...
I'm the only one in my family who's...
我...我就是...
I-I just can't...
怎么努力都没有用
It doesn't make any difference anyway.
I...
霍兰先生,我正要找你
Mr. Holland! Just the man I was looking for.
我们正为明年的课程筹组教材委员会
想听下你的意见,下周二晚开会
We're forming a textbook committee for next year's curriculum.
And I would like to have your ideas and suggestions.
抱歉,雅各布斯夫人,周二晚上我没空
- We meet next Tuesday night in the library. - Oh, I'm sorry, Mrs. Jacobs.
我观察你四、五个月了,霍兰先生
- I'm very busy on Tuesday night. - Uh- huh.
You know, for a good four or five months now, I've been watching you, Mr. Holland.
一放学你就冲向停车场
比你的学生跑得还快
I've never seen a teacher sprint for the parking lot after last period...
也许你更适合当我们的田径教练
with more speed and enthusiasm than his students.
雅各布斯夫人,我每天早晨是否准时到校?
Perhaps you should be our track coach.
Mrs. Jacobs, I get here on time every morning, don't I?
我对工作尽心尽力
老师的任务有二:传授知识
I'm doing my job the best I can.
A teacher is two jobs. Fill young minds with knowledge, yes.
但更重要是给他们指引方向
以免妄用知识
But more important, give those minds a compass...
我不知你传授知识做得怎么样,霍兰先生
so that that knowledge doesn't go to waste.
不过指南针作用，尚未得见
Now, I don't know what you're doing with the knowledge, Mr. Holland...
but as a compass you're stuck.
我恨死那女人!我更厌恶教书,艾莉丝
I really hate that woman. And I hate teaching, Iris. I hate it.
谁也教不好这些孩子!
我不知该怎么办
Nobody could teach these children. Nobody.
他们就只是呆坐在那儿望着我.心不在焉…
I don't know what I'm gonna do.
They just sit there staring up at me.
以前演出环境再差,听众不专心，你会罢演离开吗?
There's no there there. I've been trying to teach them...
Listen, you've played a lot of tough houses.
等等,我们不是同一国的吗?
- When they didn't listen, did you quit and go home? - Wait a minute.
我是支持你的
- Or keep playing? - Wait. Aren't we supposed to be on the same side?
只是…我…
I am. It's just that I...
我…
什么?
I...
What?
我怀孕了
I'm pregnant.
本来不是很确定,但是我去看了医生... 结果证实了
I wasn't... I wasn't sure if I was.
But I went to the doctor and I...
I am.
我们要有孩子了
We are.
你说话呀
S...
Say something.
Wow.
艾莉丝…
Iris.
-艾莉丝… -我有了,我就知道…
-你会不高兴,但是… -艾莉丝,只是吓一跳,没别的
I... I don't know. I knew...
- I knew you wouldn't be, but I just... - Iris.
- Iris, it just took me by surprise. That's all. - I just hoped you...
讲个故事给你听好吗?
Let me tell you a story, okay?
我15岁时常在一家唱片店玩
When I was 15 years old, I used to hang out at a local record store.
有个店员,自以为懂我的口味，给了我一张唱片
And there was this guy who worked there who...
是约翰?柯尔的音乐  (爵士乐即兴演奏创始人之一,1967年去世)
you know, thought he knew what I liked and he handed me this album one day.
于是我拿回家来听
And it was John Coltrane.
我不喜欢 我真的很讨厌那音乐!
So I took it home, and I put it on the machine.
And I hated it. I mean, I really hated it.
我根本听不懂
I just didn't get it.
于是…我又听了一次
So I...
一遍又一遍…
played it again.
I played it again, and I played it again.
后来，我止不住地播放它
And then, I just couldn't stop playin' it.
聆听着每个音符
I kept listening to those notes.
然后我明白…那正是我终生要做的事业
And I realized that...
that's what I wanted to do with the rest of my life.
你明白吗?
创作音乐
You know?
Make music.
[Sighs]
Tsk. [Sighs]
我想说的是…
What am I tryin' to say?
艾莉丝,当你说…
我们要有孩子了
Look, Iris.
Look, you... You tell me that...
we're gonna have a baby.
Well...
这就好像…跟约翰?柯尔再谈一次恋爱…
that's like falling in love with John Coltrane...
all over again.
就算你说谎,也是最美丽的谎言
If that is a lie...
that is the sweetest lie I ever heard.
请大家坐好
- [Bell Rings] - Let's take our seats, please.
谁能说出爱奥尼亚音阶和多里安音阶的分别?
Anybody here know the difference between the Ionian and the Dorian scale?
谁知道?
- [Girl] Uh-yeah. - Anybody?
我只想证实…
[Chuckles]
五个月来我没有让你们有丝毫的长进
I just wanted to confirm the fact that...
I've made absolutely no impact on you in the last five months.
沙利文先生
Mr. Sullivan.
你喜欢哪类音乐?
Yeah?
What kind of music do you like to listen to?
大胆讲
- Um... - Don't be afraid.
摇滚乐
Rock and roll.
-你呢? -摇滚乐
- What about you? - Rock and roll.
-你呢? -古典音乐
马屁精
- You? - Classical.
Brownnoser.
有人喜欢巴赫吗?
[Students Laughing]
Does anybody here like Johann Sebastian Bach?
除了你?
我相信大家...无论知道与否...都对巴赫的音乐有好感
Other than you.
I'll bet all of you, whether you know it or not...
already like Johann Sebastian Bach.
Dd
-这首曲名叫什么? -“恋人协奏曲”
What's this called?
-谁写的? -玩具合唱团
[Together] "Lover's Concerto. "
- Who wrote it? - The Toys.
错了!
Wrong.
这是G大调小步舞曲,作曲者是巴赫
That was "Minuet in G. "
And it was written by Johann Sebastian Bach.
听出来了吗?
You hear it?
Bum-bum-bum-bum-bum dd
他在1725年写的
And he wrote it in 1725.
这两首曲子都是爱奥尼亚音阶的典型例子
They are both prime examples of the Ionian scale.
现在听听这个,看看你们能不能... 听得出来 这支曲… 和刚才那支有何关连?
Now, listen, and see if you can hear the connective tissue...
between what I just played and this.
（摇滚乐）
[Rock And Roll]
Dd
[Holland] Whoo!
他们把手举到半空，争相发言
And their hands were up in the air and they were answering questions.
真好玩，真过瘾
And it was so much fun. It was rowdy, you know.
真是太棒了
It was... It was just great.
嘿嘿嘿,让我们瞧瞧...
只返工两次,用了三小时就拼好了
Hey, hey, hey. Let... What do we think, huh?
And it only took two tries and three hours.
你忘记你有一个心灵手巧的老公了吗
但现在我们真的好挤
Well, you didn't realize you'd married such a handy man, did ya?
But now we really don't have any space.
Oh.
我们找栋大房子怎么样?
Well, how would you feel if we moved into a house?
-你开玩笑? -是真的
You're kidding.
我们租不起
No.
But we can't afford that.
动用积蓄就租得起，暑假我还教人开车
If we used our savings account we could...
- 今年暑期你要专心作曲 - 我们会想到办法的
and I taught driver's ed during the summer.
- You were gonna only compose this summer. - Well, we could make it work.
-意思是拆掉婴儿床? -绝对不拆!
That'd mean taking the crib apart again.
我会先拆墙
Never. [Laughs]
I'll tear a wall down first.
由你决定
It's up to you.
-我们搬家吧 -真的吗?
- I think we should do it. - Really!
弹奏你写的那首令我爱上你的歌
Play the song you wrote that made me fall in love with you.
令你爱上我的歌?
- The song that made you fall in love with me? - Mm-hmm.
那首令你...对了!那首歌
The song that made you... Oh! Yes, the song.
- "赐我一个勇敢的男人..." - 不是这个
# Give me some men who are stouthearted... - No! No!
-不是吗? -不是,,快弹嘛!
- No? - No. Come on.
Dd
-霍兰先生? -你迟到了
你把单簧管忘在这儿了
- Mr. Holland? - You're late.
是的,如果你知道有谁想要...
And you left your clarinet here the other day.
Yeah, um, if you know anyone who wants it...
我想退出，我只会拖大家的后腿
I'm giving up the clarinet.
我只是来跟你说谢谢 谢谢你帮我
I'm just... I'm just goofing everybody else up anyway.
So, um, I just wanted to say thanks.
Thanks for trying.
吹单簧管好玩吗?
Is it any fun?
那是我的愿望
I wanted it to be.
我想，我们采用的方法不对
我们只是照着谱吹
You know what we've been doing wrong, Miss Lang?
We've been playing the notes on the page.
还有什么别的方法?
[Machine Clicks]
Well, what else is there to play?
音乐不仅是记载在乐谱上的
Well, there's a lot more to music than notes on a page.
（国王乐队的摇滚颂歌“Louie Louie"）
例如这个合唱组合
[The Kingsmen: "Louie, Louie"]
他们唱得不怎么样
These guys, for example.
也不懂和声技巧
Now, they can't sing.
And they have absolutely no harmonic sense.
他们不断重复这三个和弦
And they're playing the same three chords over and over again.
但是我喜欢
And I love it.
-你呢? -喜欢
- Do you? - Yeah.
喜欢!
为什么?
[Chuckles] Yeah. Why?
[Record Continues]
-我不知道. -你知道的
I don't know.
-因为很好玩? -没错
- Yeah, ya do. - Because it's fun?
因为音乐表演应该是好玩的
That's right. Because playing music...
它是关于情感的
is supposed to be fun.
关于感受的,能感动别人的，生活中美好的东西
It's about heart.
It's about feelings and moving people...
它不只是印在纸上的音符!
and something beautiful in being alive.
我能教你书本上的符号,表达情感却无可言传
And it's not about notes on a page. I could teach you notes on a page.
I can't teach you that other stuff.
帮我个忙
- [Record Continues] - Do me a favor.
拿起单簧管和我一起演奏
- Pick up your clarinet and play with me. - Okay.
这一次不看谱
-我不行… -你早已熟悉了它
- And this time no music, - Oh!
它已经在你脑海、指间和心里
Because you already know it.
你只是不相信自己
It's already in your head and your fingers and your heart.
You just don't trust yourself to know that.
好吧,我们开始
准备好了吗?
Okay, here we go.
一,二,三,四…
Ready?
One, two, three, four.
[Music]
没事,我们再来
- [Note Cracks] - Ah! - Okay.
这次不要把吹口含得太深
Let's do it again, and this time not so much lip on the mouthpiece.
好
一,二,三,四…
- Okay. - One, two, three, four.
[Music]
没关系,不不,别丧气
- [Note Cracks] - Oh!
All right. No, no, don't do that.
-我问你个问题 -什么?
- Let me ask you a question. - What?
当你照镜子时,最喜欢自己哪一部分?
When you look in the mirror...
what do you like best about yourself?
我的头发
My hair.
为什么?
Why?
我爸说那使他想起晚霞
Well, my father always says that it reminds him of a sunset.
那好,让我们吹出晚霞吧
Play the sunset.
闭上眼
Close your eyes.
一,二,三,四…
One, two, three, four.
Dd
不要停下来!
[Laughing] Don't stop playing.
[Piano Stops, Clarinet Continues]
[Clarinet Continues]
“横幅:祝1965年毕业班好运”
Dd
dd
（约翰逊总统） “我何尝忍心…”
[Lyndon Johnson] I do not find it easy...
“把优秀的美国子弟…送上战场”
to send the flower of our youth...
“但只要世上有心存仇恨和破坏的人”
our finest young men, into battle.
But as long as there are men who hate and destroy...
“我们就要奋勇抵抗”
[Helicopter Whirring] We must have the courage to resist.
“我们将派军进驻越南” （1965年美国以"滚石行动"全面介入越战）
We will stand...
in Vietnam.
别紧张,单脚踩踏板
单脚踩!
Just relax. Try to use one foot.
双脚松开  对!就这样
Try to use one foot!
单脚.单脚.对啦!
Try to get two feet off! That's it! Right! Right!
“keep on runnin'”
One foot! One foot! That's it!
“keep on hidin'”
# Keep on runnin' #
你开得有点太快!
# Keep on hidin' #
Uh, you're goin' a little too fast.
有点太快,不太稳!
A little too fast. A little too erratically.
A little too erratically.
靠右一点!
Just a little to the right... Oh!
“keep on runnin'”
好吧,这次我们学到什么经验?
# Keep on runnin' #
“Runnin' from my arms”
Okay, what have we learned from this?
“快捷搬家公司”
# Runnin' from my arms #
“One fine day I'm gonna be the one”
# One fine day I'm gonna be the one #
“To make you understand”
# To make you understand #
“Oh,yeah I'm gonna be your man”
# Oh, yeah I'm gonna be your man #
[Classical]
[Horn Honking]
噢!霍兰先生,你闯红灯了
Whoa. That was a... That was a stop sign you went through back there, Mr. Holland.
-你肯定是超速了 霍兰先生 -是的
- You're definitely speeding, Mr. Holland. - Yeah.
- [Tires Screeching] - [Laughing]
[Horn Honking]
我想交通规则也不允许从右侧超车
I don't think you're just allowed to just pass on the right like that either.
- [Tires Screeching] - [Horns Honking]
天啊!
- Geez! - [Front Seat Student Gasps]
-这是单行道  -闭嘴,何思塔先生!
This is a one-way street, Mr. Holland.
- Mr. Hosta! Shut up! - [Horns Honking]
[Whimpers]
产科病房...
[Panting] Um, um, Maternity. Thank you.
谢谢!
[Babies Crying]
“霍兰”
205室
[Mouthing Words]
[Knocking]
艾莉丝!
Iris.
来看看你的儿子
柯尔?霍兰
Come meet your son.
-你怎么样? -还好!
Coltrane Holland.
- How you doin'? - Okay.
瞧!
[Whispering] Look.
-可以吗? -当然
- [Cooing] - Can I?
Sure.
噢!
Oh!
他真可爱
He's beautiful.
- [Yawning] - [Laughing]
[Sputtering]
[Coughing]
“有位老太太,把苍蝇吞下肚”
[Piano]
I know an old lady who swallowed a fly
“为何吞苍蝇,我不明白”
I don't know why she swallowed that fly
“或许她会活不下来”
“有位老太太,把蜘蛛吞下肚”
Perhaps she'll die
- I know an old lady - [Chuckling]
“蜘蛛爬上爬下 她肚里奇痒难耐”
Who swallowed a spider
That wiggled and jiggled
And tickled inside her
“吞下蜘蛛去抓苍蝇”
She swallowed the spider to catch the fly
“但为何吞苍蝇,我不明白”
I don't know why
- [Laughing] - She swallowed that fly
“或许她会活不下来”
这孩子有音乐天份
Perhaps she'll die The kid is a natural.
一定是怀他时  你放的那些胎教音乐
It must have been all that music you played at my stomach while I was pregnant.
各位,无线电城音乐厅荣誉推出
[Upbeat Jazz]
Ladies and gentlemen, Radio City Music Hall...
柯尔?格什温?霍兰! (都是音乐大师的名字)
is proud to present Coltrane Gershwin Holland.
Dd
霍兰先生,我注意到…
你在教学生摇滚乐
Mr. Holland, it has come to my attention...
that you are teaching the students rock and roll.
-这有问题吗? -"有问题吗?" 是的,我认为有
- Is this a problem? - "Is this a problem?" Yes, I think so.
我们唯一的职责是教学
如果没纪律,老师没法教,学生没法学
Our only job is to teach.
We cannot teach and the students cannot learn if there is no discipline.
抱歉,你究竟想说什么,吉恩?
Uh, I'm sorry, uh, what exactly is your point, Gene?
我是说,这种涣散的音乐会导致秩序的败坏
My point is, rock and roll by its very nature leads to a breakdown in discipline.
你要我怎么做? 要我只当摇滚乐不存在?
What would you like me to do? Deny that rock and roll exists?
我认为...我们认为你应该教授古典音乐
What I am... What we are saying is that you should be pushing the classics.
布拉姆斯,莫扎特.以及史特拉文斯基
Brahms, Mozart, Stravinsky.
说到秩序的瓦解,史特拉文斯基的音乐正是推翻沙皇的音乐
Stravinsky was the music of the Russian Revolution...
-你夸大其词. -那么,"金斯顿三重唱" 如何?
if you want to talk about a breakdown in discipline.
- You are deliberately exaggerating. - How about the Kingston Trio?
- "和米奇一起唱"(唱片名)又怎么说? - 二位,等一下!
- How about Sing Along With Mitch? - Oh, please!
霍兰先生 我不想干涉任何老师的教学
Just a minute, gentlemen.
Mr. Holland, I do not want to interfere in the curriculum of any teacher.
但是下周我要和校董开会
But next week I have a meeting with the school board.
有些董事深信摇滚是"魔鬼之音"
And there are people in this community who believe...
that rock and roll is a message sent from the devil himself.
那么当提及这话题 我该如何对他们说?
Now when that issue comes up, what can I tell them?
雅各布斯夫人
Mrs. Jacobs, you tell them...
你告诉他们…我是在教音乐
that I am teaching music...
从贝多芬到比利·哈乐黛（爵士歌星）再到摇滚乐
and that I will use anything...
from Beethoven to Billie Holiday to rock and roll...
只要能让学生爱上音乐 我都乐于采用
if I think it'll help me teach a student... to love music.
你的回答...
That's...
合情合理 霍兰先生
a reasonable answer, Mr. Holland.
我可以向校董会交代了
I can tell them that.
还有事吗?
Was there something else?
有…
本赛季你有没有去看过球赛?霍兰先生
Yes, um, have you been...
to any of the football games this season, Mr. Holland?
说不上有,没看过
雅各布斯夫人和我都觉得赛场少了点什么
I can't say that I have. No.
Well, Mrs. Jacobs and I feel that there's something missing.
触地得分?
Touchdowns. [Laughing]
对不起
I'm sorry. [Laughing]
关于军乐队,你了解多少?
What do you know about marching bands?
您说什么?
Pardon me?
准备!开始!
Blue, 32! Set, hut!
扑他!扑倒他!
[Grunting]
-(霍兰先生)嘿嘿嘿 -就是这样!这才叫擒抱
Get him! Get him down! [Whistle Blows]
[Coach Meister] That's the way.
- [Mr. Holland] Hey, hey, hey. - That's the way to crash down.
鼓和低音号
Uh, drums and sousaphones.
排在这里,低音号站两侧
Come on, line up here. Sousaphones on either side.
中音号,萨克斯,在第三列
And, baritones, and, and saxes.
衣服塞进去!这不是开派对!
Here. Third line.
那也不是礼服,给我塞进去!
Put your shirttail in! This isn't a dance.
稍微快些,我们不想在这儿耗到天黑
It looks like a party dress. Get it in!
Let's do it a little quicker. You know, we don't wanna be here 'til it's dark.
我们人数不是偶数 我想…
Now, we're not... We're not even.
你在这里取齐 …
I'd like to make some attempt to, um...
你明白我说"取齐"的意思吗?
Can you even up here? Can you, like, even this...
排成一排...对了
Do you understand what I'm saying when I say "even up"?
好了,下次要注意取齐
Line up. There you go.
All right, all right. Take care of even some... next time.
过来!他们在那边,你却在这里,你在搞什么?
-对不起. -你想气死我吗?
- Get over here! - All right.
They're over there. You're over here. What are you doing?
看我的手势,好吗?
- Sorry, Coach. - Are you trying to kill me?
一,二,三,齐步走!
Watch my hand, okay?
One, two, three, march.
左,右,左,右,左,右…
Left, right, left, right, left, right, left, right.
不,不对!
- Left, right, left, right. - [Boy Murmuring] This is stupid.
-左,右,左,右,左,右,对  -约翰,球队单膝下跪休息
No, no, no. Left, right, left, right.
不对,挤成一团了
- Left, right, left, right. - Hey, John, let 'em take a knee.
不,不,大家散开,散开!
No, no, no. We're clumping. You're clumping up.
散开!散开!
No, no, no, people. Spread out. I want you to spread!
然后转过来,转过来继续
- [Boy] He said "spread. " - Spread out. Spread.
And turn. Turn around and keep marching.
齐步走!左,右,左,右…
Keep marching. Left, right, left, right.
Left, right, left, right. Left...
停!单膝下跪休息
[Sighs]
[Whistle Blowing] Stop! Take a knee.
好了,跑步去,戴上头盔!
- [Football Players Laughing] - All right, start runnin'.
哨音没响不准停
Hats on! And don't stop 'til you hear this whistle.
格伦,格伦
Glenn. Glenn.
好家伙,真要命!
Man, oh, man, oh, man. Oh, man!
我猜你从未在军队呆过
I take it you were never in the army.
还用问吗?
[Both Laugh]
Now, that's a stupid question.
我服过役,齐步走,练得我快累死了
I was. Man, I marched my keister off.
那就帮帮我啊
Well, then, help me out.
好哇!
看到看台上那个孩子了吗?他叫卢拉斯
Okay. You see this kid up in the stands here?
是本校有史以来最好的中卫  因为功课不好,被我赶出队
That's Lou Russ. He was the greatest halfback this school ever had.
现在连摔跤队也不能待了
I had to toss him off the team because of his grades.
你想我怎样?要我代他去考试?
Now I'm about to lose him for wrestling if I don't get 'em up.
Bill, what are we talkin' about? What do you want me to do? Take his tests for him?
不是
你如果让他参加乐队
No, but I bet if he played in your band...
校长就会给他学分 我就帮你操练队伍
I could talk Jacobs into giving him an academic credit...
-他会什么乐器? -都不会
and then I'll help ya out here.
- What instrument does he play? - He doesn't.
一样也不会
He doesn't play anything. [Laughing]
-你开玩笑吗? -不,他会适应的
What? Are you kidding?
格伦 你让他随便玩个乐器…
No, he'll fit right in.
Glenn, listen, you get him to play anything...
我就教他们走步
and I'll get them to march.
各位,我是麦斯特教练,来陪你们操练
Ladies and gentlemen, I'm Coach Meister...
拉斯先生,你对音乐有何认识?
your marching buddy.
- 没有!教练先生  - 你不用再加一个"先生",我也不是教练
- You know anything at all about music, Mr. Russ? - No, sir, coach.
就叫我霍兰先生吧
You don't have to say "sir, " and I'm not a coach.
对不起,先生... 我是说,霍兰先生
So Mr. Holland is just fine.
不用道歉,你没做错什么
Sorry, sir... I mean, Mr. Holland.
Don't apologize. You haven't done anything yet.
你会看乐谱吗?哪怕一丁点?
Um, you know how to read music even a little?
-不会 -不会 -不会
- No. - No.
你要明白...
No.
Well, you do realize that you're gonna have to learn...
你至少要懂一些音乐的基本常识...才能加入乐队
at least some of the fundamentals of music...
霍兰先生 我会努力
before you can get into the band.
Listen, Mr. Holland. I'll work hard.
我知道该如何努力 只是我不是读书的材料
I know how to work hard. I'm just not a school type of person.
好吧
那么,你想玩什么乐器?
Okay.
Well, which instrument do you think you'd like to play?
嗯,我想过...电吉他如何?
Well, I was kind of thinkin' like... How about electric guitar?
这是军乐队,吉他电线会绊倒人的
Well, this is a marching band. The extension cord would kill us.
-吹大号如何? -那是满脸痘痘的胖子吹的!
How about the tuba?
嗯,留给你上手的时间有限 打鼓好吗?
Tubas are for fat guys with pimples.
Well, given the time constraints, how do drums strike you?
打鼓?
A drum!
（"星条旗永不落"）
["The Stars And Stripes Forever"]
[Humming Along]
打得太快了,拉斯先生!
- You're ahead, Mr. Russ! - [Beating Out Of Rhythm]
跟着拍子,拉斯先生!
Get on the beat, Mr. Russ.
停,停,停…
Bum, ba, bum, ba... Whoa, whoa, stop, stop.
-怎么了?干嘛不打了? -我不知道该到哪里了
Stop, stop, stop, stop. What happened? Where did you go?
那就去找出来
I keep losin' my place.
Well, why don't you find it?
不少人没有节拍概念
Enough of us here already think that time is a magazine.
你也不要再雪上加霜,顺便说一句...
巴尔先生,演奏中倾倒乐器里的口水
And I don't want you confusing us any further. And by the way...
Mr. Barr, it is not...
是一件很失礼的事…
as they say, considered couth...
to empty your spit valve in the middle of the performance...
尤其倒在邻座同学的脚上
especially not on the foot of the person sitting next to you.
我们从头再来,一,二,一,二
Okay, let's, uh, take it again from the top.
One, two, one, two.
Bum-bum-bum
噢,噢!噢,噢!停,停!
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa!
Whoa, whoa, whoa! Stop, stop, stop.
铃声救了你们!明天同一时间同一地点见,谢谢!
[Bell Rings]
Boy, were you saved by the bell. All right, same time...
same place tomorrow.
-霍兰先生,我想让你知道... -你会很努力,我知道
Thank you very much.
Mr. Holland, look, I just want you to know that...
-谢谢,霍兰先生 -不客气
That you're gonna work very hard. I know, Louis. Thank you.
- Thanks, Mr. Holland. - You're welcome.
说说你巡回演出时的艳遇吧!
Will you tell me some stories about the chicks you met when you were on the road?
那是不同的年代,不同的我
- That was a different time. I was a very different guy. - Mm-hmm.
将军!
- Check. - [Exhales]
Oh, you must be keepin' something so good for me...
你一定对我隐瞒着什么
你总是躲避这类话题
because you're always avoiding this line of questioning.
我没有躲避,只是我已过上另一种生活
- [Laughs] I'm not avoiding anything. - I know you are.
我有美丽的妻子,可爱的小孩,你不了解的
- It's just, I lead a very different life now. - Uh-huh.
I have a beautiful wife, a gorgeous child. Something you know nothing about. Check.
将军
-有一天我也会有孩子 -你要先娶个老婆
- I want to have kids someday. - You ought to find a wife first.
我没那么急迫
- I don't want kids that badly. - [Laughs]
将军,死棋
Checkmate.
好吧 好吧
[Sighs] All right, all right, all right.
何况,学校的孩子就像我的儿女
Besides, the kids at school are like my kids.
有时我也想揍他们 但更希望他们有出息
I wanna smack 'em sometimes, but mostly I just want to see 'em do good.
卢拉斯能不能加入军乐队?
So, Lou Russ. He gonna make it?
有没有可能?
Is he gonna make it?
-我看是不行. -别这样,我需要他!
I don't think so.
不能摔跤并非世界末日
Glenn, come on. I need him!
[Chuckles] A kid doesn't wrestle, it's not the end of the world.
对他来说是,他只会摔跤
For him, it is. If he doesn't wrestle, he doesn't have anything else.
不关摔跤的事,我是关心他
It's not about wrestling. I care about the kid.
他不会乐器,我怎么留他?
Bill, how am I supposed to keep a kid in the band if he can't play an instrument?
你教他呀!像拉斯这么努力的孩子
You teach him. You're telling me that you cannot teach a willing kid like Lou Russ...
你没法教会他打鼓?
-我尽力了! -教他!
- to bang a drum or something? - I tried!
-教不会呀! -那你是个不称职的老师
- No, no, you teach him. - I tried and I can't.
我不能坐视他错过机会
Well, then, you're a lousy teacher.
And I just can't see a chance like this gettin' away from him if I can stop it.
我年青时也跟他一样
要不是有人给我机会发挥所长
Look, I was a kid just like him.
And if someone hadn't given me a chance to excel in the one thing I was good at...
我永远不会像现在这样 成为一名出色的教练
I never would have become the brilliant gum-chewing coach that I am.
[Chuckles]
象棋队一直不收我,毁了我的生活
I was kept off the chess team, and, well, it's ruined my life.
[Laughs]
再下一盘
Do it again. Come on.
[Stevie Wonder]
[Stevie Wonder] # Baby, everything is all right #
# Uptight Outta sight #
# Baby, everything is all right #
# A poor man's son from across the railroad track #
# Only shirt I own is here on my back #
# But I'm the envy of every single guy #
# Since I'm the apple of my girl's eye #
# When we do our stuff go downtown for a while #
# Money's goin' My suits aren't in style #
# But it's all right if my clothes aren't new #
# Out of sight Because my heart is true #
# She says, baby everything is all right #
# Uptight Clean outta sight #
# She's a pearl of a girl I guess that's what you might say #
# I guess her folks brought her up that way #
# On the right side of the tracks she was born and raised #
# In a great big old house full of brothers #
# And then she says, baby everything is all right #
["The Stars And Stripes Forever"]
噢,噢,噢!停,停,停,停,停!
Da-da-da, da-da-da
拉斯先生
Whoa, whoa, whoa! Stop, stop, stop, stop, stop.
恭喜你,你跟上节拍了!
- Mr. Russ. - [Groans]
Congratulations, you found the beat.
[Applauding, Cheering, Blowing Instruments]
“真是美好的一天 巡游非常精彩”
[Announcer] It's a wonderful day and a terrific parade.
“现在开过来的是 原装1937年道奇牌校车”
And here comes an original 1937 Dodge school bus.
“后边的是"春之公主"花车”
And there is the princess of spring, Tammy Monroe.
“她真是美极了”
She is just great.
“飞吻满天飞”
- Hiya! Here you go. - Kisses, kisses, kisses to blow all around!
“这真是令人心醉的周末”
Isn't this a great way to spend a weekend?
“我最爱的温哥华堡高中军乐队过来了”
Oh, here comes my favorite: The Fort Vancouver High School Marching Band...
“由我的好友吉姆率领的百人团队”
led by my friend Jim; over 100 instruments.
[Band Playing, Crowd Cheering]
别忘了,盯住前面队员的鞋子
Don't forget I want you to keep your eyes on the shoes of the person in front of you.
记住了?玩得开心点! 准备好没有?
All right. Have a good time. Ready?
不,不!退回去!(-肯尼迪高中,到这边来) 退后,退后,别紧张!
No, no! No, no, no, no, no! Back.
- [Official] Kennedy High, get in there. - Back, back, back. Just relax.
- 出发了! - 深呼吸,我们会玩得很开心的
- Let's go! - Just take a deep breath. We're gonna have fun.
- 出发,肯尼迪高中! - 我们已经尽快了,妈的!
- Let's go, Kennedy! - We're doing the best we can, damn it!
等一下,等一下
Hold it. Hold it.
班森先生,预备?
Ready? Mr. Benson.
一,二,三,四
- One, two, three, four! - [Drums Beating Cadence]
[Whistle Blowing]
[Cheering]
["Louie, Louie"]
“现在有真正精彩节目上演”
[Announcer] Now we have a real treat coming down the road:
“约翰?F?肯尼迪高中的军乐队”
The John F. Kennedy Marching Band.
“精彩吧?”
“这是他们首次参加巡游 由格伦?霍兰先生带队”
- [Cheering] - And aren't they good!
Their first year in this parade, led by Glenn Holland.
Yea!
- [Laughing] - Hey!
那是我儿子,我儿子!路易!
That's my boy! That's my boy!
路易!
Hey, Louis! Louis! Louis!
Louis! [Laughs]
- Hey! - Yeah!
[Fire Truck Horn Blasting]
[Baby Crying]
艾莉丝!
Iris. Cole.
柯尔!
游行好玩吗?
Was that fun or what?
柯尔有点不太对劲
There's something wrong with Cole.
-怎样? -不知道,但我用尽办法
I don't know, but I've... I've tried different things.
从背后吓他…敲锅子,大声喊他名字…
Um, sneaking up behind him and...
跺脚
banging pots and screaming his name and stomping on the floor.
我跺脚他才回头.咧嘴笑,以为我在跟他玩
He... He turned when I did that. Big smile.
艾莉丝
- He thought I was playing a game. - Iris.
我猜他听不见
I don't think he can hear.
柯尔!
Cole?
柯尔?
[Clapping] Cole?
Cole! [Clapping]
柯尔?
Cole? [Clapping]
柯尔有90%听力受损
Cole has a 90% hearing loss.
如果加以训练 他会学会利用那仅剩余的听力
Now, with training he will learn to use what hearing he has left.
像对正常小孩一样待他 即使他听不见也要跟他讲话
Treat him as if he's normal. Talk to him as if he can hear you.
我注意到柯尔习惯用手势来表达
I notice Cole uses gestures to help himself be understood.
我提醒你们不要用手势来回应
Let me caution you, don't use them back.
手势表达无助于帮他立足社会
Gestures won't help him find his place in a hearing world.
等他大一点,有专门学校教他讲话
When he's older, there are schools that will help him and you to find his voice.
（贝多芬"A大调第七交响曲"）
[Beethoven: "Symphony No. 7 In A Major"]
他听不见
芸芸众生之中,偏偏是他 一点都听不见
He couldn't hear.
Of all people.
Not a thing.
正因为贝多芬听不见
And because Beethoven couldn't hear, the thought of him conducting...
绝大多数人都认为他的指挥或作曲...乏善可陈
or let alone composing... was pathetic to most people.
为了回应这些人 他谱写了第七交响乐,并指挥公演
And so to answer them, he composed and conducted the "Seventh Symphony. "
[Continues]
想想看…
Just try to imagine...
贝多芬站在指挥台上…
Beethoven standing on that podium...
手执指挥棒…
holding his baton...
优雅地挥舞着双手…
his hands waving gracefully through the air...
心中的乐团正完美地演出
and the orchestra in his mind...
is playing perfectly.
而他面前的乐团…却拚命地在跟上他的节拍
And the orchestra in front of him...
trying desperately just to keep up.
还有个故事…
[Clicks Tongue] There is a story...
为了创作…
that in order to write his music...
贝多芬断然锯掉钢琴脚
Beethoven literally sawed the legs off his piano...
使琴身贴在地板上
so that he could lay the body flat on the ground.
然后…
And then...
他躺在钢琴旁边,耳朵紧贴着地板
he would lay down on the ground next to the piano...
with his ear pressed to the floor.
用手指敲打键盘…
And he would pound the keys with his fingers...
想靠着感受地板的震动听到音乐
in order to hear his music through the vibrations...
霍兰先生...?
of the floor.
Mr. Holland? Mr. Holland?
霍兰先生...?
如果他听不见  怎么辨别音调?
If he couldn't hear, how would he even know what the notes were?
比如,如果他从来没有听过C调 那他怎么知道他想要的是什么调?
Like, if he never heard a "C... "
how'd he know that's what he wanted played?
因为…
Well...
贝多芬不是天生耳聋的
Beethoven wasn't born deaf.
[Helicopter Whirring]
[John Lennon] # Imagine there's no heaven #
“越南要和平” (1968年初美军战况惨烈，反越战游行遍及全美)
[Marchers] We want freedom!
“支持麦卡锡当总统”
# It's easy if you try # [King] Let us try to feed the hungry.
（马丁.路德.金）“让我们为饥饿的人送去食粮...”
（鲍比.肯尼迪） “我希望民主党...”
[King's Speech Continues]
# No hell below us # [Bobby] I want the Democratic Party...
（美国宇航局）“火箭升空了”
- [NASA Official] We have liftoff. - Above us only sky
（1969.7.20登月成功）“这是个人的一小步,人类的一大步...”
[Neil Armstrong] One small step for man...
# Imagine all the people #
# Livin' for today #
# Ahh #
（1969.8.15第一届Woodstock音乐节 主题"和平,反战,博爱,平等）
# Imagine there's no country #
# It isn't hard to do #
# Nothin' to kill or die for #
（1969.5 约翰?列侬和小野洋子 "为和平而卧床七天"）
（1969.1.20尼克松当选第37任总统 美军开始撤出越南）
# And no religion too #
# Imagine all the people #
（嬉皮文化盛行）
# Livin' life in peace #
（巴赫: "沉睡者苏醒"）
[Bach: "Sleepers Wake"]
我们来晚啦
[Mouthing Words]
[Music Stops]
私立学校?
[Glenn] A private school?
她说那是最好的学校 在本州名列前茅
She said it's the best, and it's way ahead of any other school in the state.
-学费也是最贵的. -只要是最好的…
- It's probably the most expensive place in the state. - Yeah, but if it's the best!
我只是担心钱从哪里来
I'm just a little worried about where the money's coming from, that's all.
我知道是好学校,艾利丝  只是担心钱的问题
It's probably a great place, Iris...
指给我看,亲爱的,你要什么?
- but I... I worry about the money, okay? - What do you want, honey?
你要吃甜点?这个?
Show me. Show me what you want. Want a dessert? This?
我不明白你要什么
- [Trying To Speak] - I don't... I don't know what you want.
要什么?柯尔!
- [Whining] - What? Cole.
- [Whining Continues] - Dessert? No?
甜点?
-这个吗?我不知道你要什么! -他们教手语吗?
- This? This? I don't know what you want! - So they were signing, huh?
校方很重视,还说家长也要学
The school emphasizes it, and she said it's for parents too. What? What do you want?
-你要什么? -索伦森博士说手势是…
-这不是手势，是手语! -学习手势表达…
- Dr. Sorenson said that gestures meant... - It's way more than gestures!
意味着柯尔或许永远不会读唇语或说话!
That gestures meant that Cole would never learn how to lip-read or to talk!
他现在就不会说话 他现在两、三个字都说不了!
He can barely talk now! He can't say two or three words!
艾利丝，那人可是专家
The guy is a specialist, Iris!
他只会把聋子当白痴.柯尔不是白痴
Oh, he's a specialist who thinks that deaf people are retarded...
柯尔!
- and he is not retarded; he's... Cole! - [Door Banging, Cole Wailing]
-看他要什么,给他! -我不知道他要什么,你没看出来吗?
- What does he... Give him what he wants! - I don't know what he wants!
你每天在学校都面对着正常的孩子
I don't understand what he's trying to tell me! Don't you get it?
You go off to school every day with all of your children who are normal.
我却没法跟儿子交谈!
I can't talk to my son! I don't know what he wants...
不知道他要什么,不知道他的思想和情感!
我没法跟他说我爱他!告诉他我是谁!
or what he thinks or what he feels; I can't tell him that I love him.
我要和我的儿子说话
I can't tell him who I am!
不管花多少钱.不管那庸医说什么!
I want to talk to my son!
I don't care what it costs; I don't care what the stupid doctor says is right or wrong!
我要和我的儿子说话!
I want to talk to my son! [Sobbing]
噢,柯尔
[Sobbing] Oh, Cole. Oh, Cole.
好,今天是星期几？你知道今天是星期几吗?
Okay, now we'll talk about what is today.
是星期二.对 会不会拼出来?
Can you tell me what's today? Tuesday. Good.
星…期…二
Can you spell it for me? T-U...
E-S-D-A-Y.
好极了!明天是星期几?
[Teacher] Wonderful! Now, can you tell me what is tomorrow?
正如你们看见的 我们鼓励说话和手语一起来
[Woman] We encourage talking and signing at the same time. And, as you can see...
今天他们学习的是星期和月份
today, the class is learning the days of the week and the months of the year.
请到教室外面 好吗?
Would you care to step out for just a moment? Shall we?
-星期三 -好极了,那么昨天是星期几?
Wednesday. Great. What is yesterday?
-能不能谈谈学费的事? -好的
- [Glenn] Can we talk about tuition? - Yes.
我们有机会获得政府补助吗?
- Is there any chance of government subsidy? - I'm afraid not.
-恐怕不行  -好吧 我们会解决的
要多久他才能学会手语?
[Iris] Well, we can handle it.
Uh, so... so how long would it be before he learns how to sign?
比你俩都快 小孩学东西很快
Well, not as long as it'll take the two of you.
而大人学 就要看用不用心了
You see, children learn very quickly, but adults...
- Well, so much depends on how much you put into it. - Mm-hmm.
什么时候上课?
下一期的家长强化培训班...在六月开课
- And... when would we begin? - Well, our next intensive program...
the one that we gear toward parents, starts in June.
为期三个月,每天三小时
It's three months, three hours every day.
父母的指导对孩子最重要
The most important teacher your child will ever have is you.
（巴赫 "G大调小步舞曲"）
[Bach: "Minuet In G Major"]
这是巴赫为谁写的?
So, who was Bach writing all this for?
狄特先生,请回答?
[Continues]
《亚当斯一家》中的的勒奇?
Mr. Tidd, care to join us?
你才是勒奇呢 你这个蠢蛋
- Uh, Lurch in the Addams Family? - [Students Laughing]
-看我怎么封了你那张嘴. -随时奉陪
[Softly] You're the Lurch, you dipstick.
How 'bout I shut your smart mouth, man?
狄特!再闹就罚你留校
- Anytime you wanna try. - [Glenn] Tidd!
You take one more step and you'll think you were born in detention.
回去坐好
Get back to your seat. Stadler.
史泰德勒
有时面对自己不喜欢的人 最好的方法就是忽视
Sometimes the best way to deal with a pest is to ignore them.
好了,别忘了预习280-314页…史泰德勒
- [Bell Rings] - Okay.
Don't forget pages 280 to 314 for tomorrow. Stadler.
- [Students Chattering] - [Sighs]
-又磕药了? -我没必要上这课 这些我都会
- You stoned again, Stadler? - I don't need to stay straight for this class.
我可说出所有的名字、日期... 我知道所有音阶升降,曲式,对位法...
I know this stuff. I can give you all the names and dates you want.
那又怎样?
I know all the scales, the modes, counterpoint...
这堂课叫"音乐欣赏" 我看不出你在欣赏什么
So what?
The name of this class is Music Appreciation. I don't see you appreciating anything.
-尽是些废话 -坐下!
- This is such lame bullshit. - Sit down.
你差这一点点就要被退学了,老弟
You are this close from being suspended, pal.
[Stadler Exhales]
你觉得自己很聪明?
[Chuckles] You think you are real smart, don't you?
好…证明给我看
Okay. Prove it.
学期结束我要你交一篇论文给我
I want a paper on my desk by the end of term.
单行距书写,篇末加注
I want it to be single-spaced; I want it to be annotated.
题目是"音乐:情感的语言"
I want the name of this report to be "Music: The Language of Emotion. "
-你不能强迫我. -看我能不能!
- You can't make me do that. - Watch me!
交了没有额外加分 但不交你肯定不及格
This is not extra credit. You don't do it, you flunk.
霍兰先生,这不公平!
This isn't fair, Mr. Holland.
-人生本来就不公平,老弟 -霍兰先生?
- Life is not fair, pal. - [Door Opens]
Mr. Holland?
知道了
Yeah.
-告诉雅各布斯夫人,我会参加的 -好的
You can tell Mrs. Jacobs I'll take care of it.
-我可以走了吗? -不
- Am I released yet? - No.
星期六上午十点来这里见我
I want you to meet me here Saturday morning at 10:00 a. m.
做什么?
做一次考察
- Why? - Research.
认识他我们倍感荣幸与自豪
We are honored and we are proud that we have known him.
我们的一生从而改变
And our lives are forever changed.
路易的天赋才华与我们同在
Louis's gifts live in each of us.
我们永远怀念他的精神,勇气和爱
Let us burn bright his spirit...
his courage, his love.
-阿门 -阿门
- Amen. - [All] Amen.
"弗朗德斯阵地上,罂粟迎风摇曳"
"In Flanders fields the poppies blow...
"十字架一行一行,一列一列"
between the crosses, row on row...
"年轻的生命就在此凋谢"
that mark our place.
"天空中,飞翔的百灵鸟勇敢歌唱"
And in the sky, the larks, still bravely singing, fly...
"大地上,隆隆枪炮还在隐约回荡"
[Speaking With Difficulty] Scarce heard among the guns below. "
他是…他是谁?
So, uh, who's the... who's the one, uh...
You know.
卢拉斯，一个曾跟我学打鼓的年轻人
Just some kid I taught to bang a drum, named Louie Russ.
他曾三度晋级州际摔跤决赛
[Poem Continues Nearby]
He made the...
state wrestling finals three years running.
他没有你聪明.千辛万苦才熬到毕业…
He was never as smart as you are.
He had to work real hard even to graduate.
或许那就是他分外珍惜的原因
Maybe that's why it meant so much to him.
举枪
[Gunshot]
放!
Aim. Fire.
举枪--放!
- [Gunshot] - Aim. Fire.
敬--礼!
[Gunshot]
Present... arms.
（小号:"时光流逝"）
[Trumpet: "Day Is Done"]
谨代表总统及我们的国家
On behalf of the president of the United States and a grateful nation...
献旗表达感激  并向为国捐躯的路易?拉斯下士表示敬意
I present this flag in recognition of your son, Corporal Louis Russ...
for his long and faithful service to his country.
向后转--向前进
About face. Forward.
现在你可以走了
You can go home now.
嗨,格伦
[Exhales] Hi, Glenn.
-你还好吗? -还好
- You okay? - Oh, yeah. Yeah, brother.
真可惜!
[Breathes Deeply]
What a waste.
我们见过太多这样的孩子了
We know too many of these kids.
好了,走吧
Come on. Let's get outta here.
约翰?肯尼迪高中 “肯尼迪老鹰队之诞生地”
[Chattering]
Son.
- Smile. - Dad.
黛西当选过爱达荷小姐
Of course, Daisy was also the former Miss Idaho.
- 真的吗? - 她的衣服是用土豆皮做的,真的 (爱达荷州主要农作物是土豆)
- Is that right? - Her dress is made of a potato skin. Seriously.
- 别胡闹了,幸会 -这是格伦
- Will you stop it? It's very nice to meet you. - This is Glenn.
- 你好 -这是艾利丝
- It's nice to meet you. - And this is Iris.
- 你好,幸会 - 幸会
- Hello. Hello, nice to meet you. - Nice to meet you.
- 柯尔,来打个招呼,这是柯尔 - 柯尔是我儿子
- Cole, say hi. This is Cole. - And Cole, my son.
-大家好! -你好
- [Mrs. Jacobs] Hello, everybody. - [All] Hi.
-霍兰先生,跟你说句话  -雅各布斯夫人,你永远不会只说一句的
- Mr. Holland, a word. - Mrs. Jacobs, with you, it's never just one word.
暑假你有什么计划?
- What are your plans for the summer? - Oh, the usual, I guess.
老规矩,教学生开车,你呢?
You know, the Clyde Crashcup School of Driver's Ed. What about you?
我会很忙,养花种草,看望孙子
Oh, I'm going to be very busy. Gardens to plant. Grandchildren to visit.
我要退休了
I'm retiring, Mr. Holland.
什么?
What?
我已经答应丈夫多年,现在是时候了
[Sighs]
I've been promising my husband for several years now.
我有东西送给你
It's time.
I have something for you.
一件纪念品,若你愿意那样称它
A momento, if you will.
（当初她曾指责霍兰先生"指引学生"不力 现赠与指南针表示对他的肯定）
[Chuckling, Sighs]
我深感荣幸
I'm honored.
霍兰先生,在本校众多老师中…
Mr. Holland...
of all the teachers here at John F. Kennedy High School...
你是我最欣赏的
you're my favorite.
[Jackson Browne] # I'm gonna rent myself a house #
# In the shade of the freeway #
（1973年初,巴黎和平协约签定 美军全部撤出越南）
# Gonna pack my lunch in the morning #
And go to work each day
慢着慢着...
# And when the evenin' goes around # [Glenn] Wait, whoa, whoa!
“因此...
# I'll go on home and lay my body down # - Therefore...
我辞去总统职务,明日中午生效” （1974年8月8日,尼克松因"水门事件"辞职）
I shall resign the presidency, effective at noon tomorrow. # And when the morning light #
（第二天,杰拉尔德?福特宣誓就任总统）
# Comes streamin' in I'll get up and do it again #
（1977年1月詹姆斯?卡特就任第39任总统）
# Amen #
The brake, the brake. You're going the wrong way! # Between the longing for love #
（1979年美国经济萧条,高通货膨胀）
# And the struggle for the legal tender #
（黑人音乐开始流行,迪斯科出现）
“标语: 迪斯科,逊!”
# Well, the Sirens sing and the church bells ring #
（音乐呈现多元化发展）
你开错路了,太快了!
# And the junkman found us # [Glenn] All right, you're going the wrong way.
You're going the wrong way! You're going too fast!
（70年代末石油危机） “告示牌：汽油售罄”
# Well, the veterans dream of the fight #
（1976年协和超音速飞机开始商业运营）
（70年代芝加哥马拉松比赛）
# Fast asleep at the traffic light #
（81年罗纳德?里根上台,第40任总统）
# And the children solemnly wait #
# For the ice-cream vendor #
“欢迎1980年毕业班返校”
# Out into the cool of the evening #
# Strolls the pretender #
# He knows that all his hopes and dreams #
# Begin and end there #
- 各位,我们继续开会 - 你来跟他说...
- All right, moving on. People, let's get through this. - But you tell him, you know?
进入下一议题
- [Teachers Chattering] - Now. People, please! If we could move on...
高年级的戏剧表演
to the next item of the agenda, which is the senior class play.
去年的“罗密欧与朱丽叶”大受欢迎…
- Now... - Oh, yes, yes. Um, after our critical success...
last year with Romeo and Juliet...
今年我和霍兰先生有新的构想
Mr. Holland and I have come up with the most wonderful idea for this year's production.
我们不去演长篇巨著 我们准备演短剧
Well, we're not doing a full production. We're going to do a revue.
歌舞剧“葛希文兄弟” 独幕剧 戏服又简单
A George and Ira Gershwin revue...
比以往花费要少得多...
- with very few costumes, one set... - Much cheaper than...
我知道有人会不高兴 但今年我们打算...全部取消高年级演出项目
I know this is going to bother some of you, but I think we have to consider...
- 你疯了不成? -各位... - 太不可思议了,我反对
cutting the senior class play altogether this year.
- Are you nuts? Yes! You know what? - People, people.
请冷静 别忘了我们开会的目的  我们要想办法为学校省钱 而非花钱
Oddly enough, it's going to bother me!
People, people. Please.
Let's keep in mind why we are here.
We're looking for things which will keep money in the school coffers, not take it away.
- 带来的后果呢? -我要对校董事会负责...
- At the expense of what? - I have a responsibility to the Board of Education...
而且我们也没有资金可用来搞这类东西
那我们教这些有什么用?
and there just isn't the money to fund programs like this; not anymore.
Then what am I doing here? I mean, why are we teaching any of this?
-这对我来说非常重要  -打扰一下,吉恩
- This is the kind of thing that's important to me. - Excuse... Excuse me, Gene.
比尔,你说?
Yes? Bill?
我可以保证今年的演出一定会赚钱
I think I can guarantee that this year's show will make money.
-继续说下去. -让我的球员们来当舞蹈演员...
- I'm listening. - What if we get some of my football players...
观众一定会蜂拥而至来看他们台上的糗样
to be the dancers in the show...
and then people will show up in droves just to see them fall on their asses.
比尔,我们不是要演一出闹剧
- [Chuckling] - Bill, I don't want to turn this into a farce.
当然,我们把他们训练成舞蹈演员
It wouldn't be a farce, because we would get them...
好得让人吃惊
to be better than the damn June Taylor Dancers, and then that'll shock the hell out of everybody.
谁来教足球队员跳舞?
Who's going to teach the football players how to dance?
我!
- Me. - [Teachers Laughing]
-你行吗? -我辅修现代舞
You?
I minored in modern dance.
他辅修现代舞
- He minored in modern dance, Gene. - [Teachers Chuckling]
真的,教练逼我们学的 这样运动才能更优雅
I did. The coach had us do it...
so we'd be more graceful.
格伦,帮我抬腿,快
- Glenn, hold my leg. Come on. - Hmm.
[All Laughing]
“口诵律诗”
# I've got rhythm #
“耳听乐曲”
# I've got music #
“佳人在侧”
# I've got my gal Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
“青青草地”
# I've got daisies #
“遍开雏菊”
# In green pastures #
“佳人在侧”
# I've got my gal Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
[Piano Continues]
-- “老爹干预,我不在意”  - 微笑!
[Sighs]
# Old man trouble I don't mind him # Smile!
“门前屋后,失其踪迹”
# You won't find him Round my door #
“口诵律诗”
[Talking, Not Singing] I got rhythm I got music
“耳听乐曲”
“佳人在侧”
# I got my gal Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
“青青草地”
# I got daisies #
“遍开雏菊”
# In green pastures #
“良人在侧 吾愿足矣”
# I got my man Who could ask for anything more #
“老爹干预,我不在意”
# Old man trouble I don't mind him #
“门前屋后,失其踪迹”
# You won't find him round my door #
“星光闪烁,星光...”
# I got starlight I got... #
“星光闪烁,美梦甜蜜”
# I got starlight I got sweet dreams #
“佳人在侧 吾愿足矣”
# [Off-key] I got my gal, who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
# Who could ask for anything more #
# Who could ask for anything more # - Huh?
如何
谢谢 非常感谢
Thank you. Thank you very much.
- 我们还缺一个女主角 - 别担心,还有几个等着试唱
[Inhales]
- We still don't have an ingenue. - Don't worry. We still have a few more people to see yet.
比利?法拉第可以演葛希文...
All right, Billy Faraday can pull off the Gershwin...
但到目前为止女主角 只能让托德?马卡姆反串
but the only ingenue we seem to have so far is ToMarkam.
我认为托德...或其父母...不会...
I really don't think that ToMarkam... or his parents...
“口诵律诗”
# I got rhythm I got music #
“耳听乐曲”
“良人在侧”
# I got my man Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
“青青草地 遍开雏菊...”
# I got daisies # Maybe it's just me...
纯属个人意见,但我想她比托德更合适
# In green pastures # but I think she's better than ToMarkam.
“良人在侧 吾愿足矣”
# I got my man Who could ask for anything more #
“老爹干预,我不在意”
# Old man trouble I don't mind him #
“门前屋后,失其踪迹”
# You won't find him round my door #
“星光闪烁,美梦甜蜜”
# I got starlight I got sweet dreams #
“良人在侧”
# I got my man Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
# Who could ask for anything more #
-非常好 你是…? -摩根，罗威娜?摩根
[Exhales]
Very good. Miss... ?
Morgan. Rowena Morgan.
非常好
Very good. You were very, very good.
你唱得非常好,非常感谢!
Thank you very much.
嘿,科学展览会怎么样?
Hey. How was the science fair?
- 你想去哪儿? -上太空
- You want to go to the what? - Stars. Cole discovered astronomy tonight.
今晚柯尔知道了天文学
噢,噢!慢一点,你快得像火箭!
Whoa. Whoa. Slow down. Slow down. You're goin' like a rocket.
他想当宇航员
He wants to be an astronaut.
很好
Good.
-谁给他灌输的这种想法? -他的老师
Who put that stuff in his head?
As a matter of fact, his teachers.
你不是说要来和我们会合吗?
- I thought you were going to meet us. - Well, I wanted to...
我想去,...但我得在周末前把曲子写完
but I had to get these orchestrations finished by the end of the week for the kids.
我们要演出葛希文音乐剧
We're gonna do a Gershwin revue.
你总是有事,对不对?
It's always something, isn't it? If it isn't a school play, it's band practice...
不是排戏  就是乐队练习
要不然就是阅卷或者辅导某个学生团体
or grading papers or some student committee needs an advisor.
-错过科技展又不是世界末日  -今早你听见我说的话了吗?
Missing the science fair isn't the end of the world.
-我都听见了 -他希望今晚你能陪他!
- Maybe you didn't hear me this morning. - I heard you. I always hear you.
He wanted you to be there tonight!
天啊!
Oh, God. You know, it's really amazing.
真令人纳闷!无论我怎么付出...怎么努力
No matter what I do, no matter how hard I try...
结果总是我的错
sooner or later anything I try turns out being wrong.
为何人家的儿子比自己的重要?
Why is every other child more important to you than your child?
-我是老师,艾莉丝. -你是他的父亲!
- I'm a teacher, Iris! - You are his father!
两者都是!
I'm both!
我这样做,会让儿子伤心 我那样做,又会令学校失望
I do one thing: I let him down.
我要怎么做才能让所有人都满意?
I do another thing: I let the school down.
-事情要分轻重缓急 -我正是这样!
How the hell am I supposed to be everything for everybody?
- You have to make priorities. - I have!
我爱我的儿子,我尽力为他做到最好
He's my son and I love him. And I do the best I goddamn can.
知道吗?你的"最好"还远远不够
Well, you know what? Your best isn't good enough.
好吧 去吧 去写你的曲子吧!
So go on. Write your music.
写我的曲子?我哪有时间呀?
[Exhales] Write my music, huh?
Write my music! When do I have time to write my music?
“可否请他快马加鞭”
# Won't you tell him please to put on some speed #
“跟着我的指引”
# Follow my lead #
“我是多么需要”
# Oh, how I need #
“一个守护我...”
# Someone to watch #
“...的人”
# Over me #
太完美了,亲爱的
-霍兰先生? -唱得好
That was perfect, darling. Mr. Holland.
-我可以跟她谈谈吗? -当然可以
- It was good. Can I talk to her for a second? - Sure.
大家先休息一下
Let's all take a break for a minute.
我已尽最大努力把它唱好
- I was trying to sing my best. - It was fine.
唱得不错 我只想问你一个问题
I just want to ask you a question.
你了解女主角的心境吗?
[Inhales]
What do you think... the girl's really feeling here?
-不了解. -非了解不可
- I don't know. - You have to know...
否则唱不好
or you can't sing it.
摩根小姐,这首歌诉说一种渴望...
This song is wistful, Miss Morgan.
在一个非常非常冷漠的世界里...
It's about a woman who is alone in a very, very cold world...
一位孤单的女子,盼望有人来拥她入怀
and all she wants more than anything is to have someone hold her close...
并且告诉她一切都会好起来
and to tell her that everything's gonna be all right.
这首歌倾诉内心深处对爱的渴望
It's about...
the need for love...
in your gut.
懂了吗?
Okay?
好 从头再来
Try it again, from the top.
这次我要低一点的调
This time I wanna do it in a lower key.
[Piano]
“古有传言 爱会迷住双眼”
# There's a saying old #
# Says that love is blind #
“常常又说 精诚所至 金石为开”
# Still we're often told #
# Seek and ye shall find #
“所以我要去寻找...”
# So I'd like to seek a certain lad #
“我心中的那个人”
# I've had in mind #
- Here you go. - [Customer] Thank you.
Okay? All right.
-霍兰先生 -摩根小姐
Hi, Mr. Holland.
你在写什么?
- Hey, Miss Morgan. - What are you working on?
没什么
[Inhales] Nothing important.
只是有时候在这里工作比在家容易
Just... Sometimes it's easier to work here than at home.
-你介意我坐下吗? -不,怎么会
- Would you mind if I join you? - No. Not at all.
要咖啡...茶?
Want some coffee... or tea?
1美元以下的随便点
- Anything under a buck. - [Laughs]
你的课总是给人深刻印象
There's something I always remembered about your class, Mr. Holland.
幽默的授课方式令人难忘
You have this very highly developed sense of humor.
谢谢
Thank you.
我喜欢上你的课以及你上课的方式
I loved your class.
The way you taught.
你爱音乐,也令我们爱上它
[Exhales] You love music and you made the kids love it with you.
-我一直想告诉你这些话 -很高兴你说了
- I always wanted to tell you that. - Well. I'm glad you did.
你现在升高年级了 有没有想过上哪所大学?
So you're a senior now. You got any ideas about where you're gonna go to college yet?
没有,我父母在城中有间餐馆
No. My mom and dad have a little restaurant downtown.
父亲希望我继承他的事业
My dad's dream. He wants me to stay and help him with it.
真的?
Really.
-你自己想做什么? -你是说...?
What do you wanna do?
What do you mean?
我是说…
Well. I mean...
如果你有一个愿望
If you had one wish, you know?
无论如何都想去做的事 那会是什么?
If you could do whatever it is that you really wanted to do, what would it be?
唱歌
Sing.
我爱唱歌胜过一切
I think I'd rather sing than do anything.
有时我梦到我站在纽约的舞台上...
Sometimes I dream about going to New York and being on the stage...
面前有成千上万观众
in front of thousands of people.
那就是我的愿望
That's what I'd wish for.
恕我多言,摩根小姐,你的天赋很高
[Inhales] Maybe I shouldn't tell you this, Miss Morgan...
but you have... a great talent.
如果你有强烈的热情和渴望…
And if you have the passion, if you have the hunger...
你就应该到纽约去...
then you ought to go to New York...
做你想做的事,不管别人怎样说
and do what you want to do, no matter what anyone tells you.
要点什么吗?
Can I get you anything?
不
No. I should get going.
我该走了
-霍兰先生,星期一见 -再见
See you Monday, Mr. Holland.
Yeah. I'll see you later.
[Plunks Discordant Notes]
柯尔
Cole. Cole. Take this stuff outside.
柯尔,把这东西拿出去 好臭
It stinks.
去把窗子打开
Go open the window for him.
嘿! 别让我为难
[Piano Resumes] Hey, don't bust my butt.
不,不,不!不,不!
No, no, no, no!
-真不敢相信! -他不是故意的
I don't believe it!
开什么玩笑?他明明是故意的!
- He didn't do it on purpose. - Are you kidding me?
Of course he did.
柯尔...快帮忙捡一下
Cole, help clean up.
小心点
Careful.
停,停
Wait. Just wait, wait, wait.
我自己来
I'll... I'll do it myself.
-帮我翻译 -他说他想帮忙
- Help me out here. - He said he's only trying to help.
越帮越忙!
Well, he's making a bigger mess than he already has!
柯尔,这是不能乱碰的,你明白吗?
This is off-limits, Cole. Do you understand?
-别碰! -你比的是“别坐下.”
- Don't touch. - That's "don't sit. "
“在崎岖的爱之旅途中”
We may never, never meet again
- “我们或许永不再相逢” - 不要赶
- On the bumpy road to love - Don't push.
“但我仍然永远永远...记着...”
Still I'll always always keep
The memory of
“你用餐的模样”
The way you hold your knife
“记着我们狂舞至深夜”
The way we danced 'til 3:00
“记着我的生命因你而改变”
The way you changed my life
怎么不唱了?
[Chuckles] Where did you go?
[Giggles]
我们到此为止好了
- I think we ought to call it quits. - Oh.
我们可不可以再唱“谁来呵护我”?
Could we work on "Someone to Watch Over Me"?
-这支歌我练了很久了 -已经很晚了
- I've been working on it. - It's pretty late.
那么下次吧
Next time, then.
这是什么?
What's this?
有一天晚上写的
Oh, that's what I was working on the other night.
这是你写的?
You wrote this?
偶尔抽空写的
Well, I... I pick at it once in a while.
能弹给我听听吗?
Would you play this for me?
好吗?
- [Chuckles] - Please.
[]
La, da, da, da
La
[Humming Along]
[Inhales]
太棒了
It's wonderful.
还有吗?
Is there more?
有
Yeah. Yeah.
还没写完
- It's just not finished. - [Door Opens]
罗微娜,你练完了没有?
[Young Man] Ro. Are you done yet?
练完了吗?
Are we?
晚安,罗微娜
Good night, Rowena.
（罗微娜之歌）
[Music]
罗微娜是谁?
- Who's Rowena? - Huh?
-啊? -罗微娜是谁?
Who's Rowena?
传奇人物 挪威神话中的女英雄
Uh... A legend. A heroine from Norse mythology.
我有本关于她的书 不知放哪儿啦
I got a book about it somewhere around here.
我想问你 我和柯尔哪天晚上看演出比较好?
I was just wondering what you thought would be a good night...
for Cole and I to come see the show.
-来看首演吧. -好,喔!不行
- Opening night. - Yeah! Er, uh, no.
周五晚我要和他老师见面
Um, I've got a meeting on Friday with Cole's teachers.
-那就星期六好了 -好的
- Saturday then. - Yes. [Chuckles]
太好了
Great.
- [Orchestra] - [Cheering, Applause]
“葛希文之夜”
（足球队员） “口诵律诗”
[Football Players] # I got rhythm I got music #
“耳听乐曲”
“佳人在侧”
# I got my gal Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
“青青草地,遍开雏菊”
# I got daisies in green pastures #
“佳人在侧”
# I got my gal Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
“老爹干预,我不在意”
# Old man trouble I don't mind him #
“门前屋后，失其踪迹”
[Calculator Beeping] You won't find him round my door
“星光闪烁”
# I got starlight I got sweet dreams #
“美梦甜蜜”
“佳人在侧”
# I got my gal Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣 吾愿足矣”
# Who could ask for anything more #
“但我仍然永远永远...记着...”
[Duet] # Still I'll always #
# Always keep the memory of #
“你用餐的模样”
# The way you hold your knife #
“记着我们狂舞至深夜”
[Boy] # The way we danced 'til 3:00 #
“记着我的生命因你而改变”
# The way you changed my life #
“不!他们无法夺走我的记忆”
# No, no, they can't take that away from me #
“不!他们无法夺走...我的记忆”
# No, they can't take that away #
# From me #
“星光闪烁”
[Football Players] # I got starlight I got sweet dreams #
“美梦甜蜜”
“佳人在侧”
# I got my gal Who could ask for anything more #
“吾愿足矣”
“吾愿…”
# Who could ask #
“足…”
# For anything #
“矣”
# Anything more #
[Applause, Cheering]
[Whistling]
太好了！
- Great! [Laughs] - [Man] Good job!
再见,莎拉
[Glenn] Good night, Sarah.
霍兰先生
Mr. Holland.
我演得如何?说真话
How was I? The truth.
十分出色
- You were great. - I owe it all to you.
-全是你的功劳. -不…
[Chuckling] No.
不
Nope.
我只不过为你伴奏而已
I just accompanied you.
霍兰先生,我要照你说的去做 我要到纽约去唱歌
Mr. Holland, I'm doing what you said.
I'm going to New York. I'm gonna be a singer.
终有一天我们会因与你相识而自豪...
[Inhales] You know, someday, we're all gonna say that we knew you when.
不,你没懂我的意思
No, you don't understand.
-我明天就走 -什么?
- I'm going tomorrow. - What?
明晚演出闭幕后 有一个舞会
There's a party at Miss Olmstead's after we close the play.
我会去向朋友们告别 他们还不知道...
I'll be there to sort of say good-bye to my friends. They don't know...
我搭午夜的公交车去纽约
but the bus leaves from downtown at midnight; I'll be on it.
罗微娜…
Rowena. [Sighs] Oh, Rowena.
喔,罗微娜…
我说你该去纽约, 不是叫你现在就去
You know, when I said that you should go to New York, I didn't mean right away.
- 你有的是时间 - 如果我等,就永远去不成
- You have so much time. - If I wait, I'll never do it.
最后还是去当服务生或店员 我必须现在就走
I'll end up waiting tables or working in some store. It has to be now.
你可以跟我一起走
You could come with me.
我知道你当我是个孩子
I know you think I'm just a kid.
-我知道你有妻室. -罗微娜…
- I know you're married and you have a son. - Rowena.
我都知道
I know.
你不明白吗?你可以写出伟大的音乐
Don't you see? You could be writing great music.
明晚,金氏杂货店门前的巴士站
The bus stops at King's Drugstore, tomorrow night.
“古有传言 爱会迷住双眼”
[Rowena] # There's a saying old #
# Says that love is blind #
“常常又说 精诚所至 金石为开”
# Still we're often told seek and ye shall find #
“所以我要去寻找...”
# So I'm going to seek a certain lad #
“我心中的那个人”
# I've had in mind #
“四处寻觅,遍寻不得”
# Looking everywhere Haven't found him yet #
“令我难以忘怀”
# He's the big affair I cannot forget #
“他是我唯一的思念 想起来就感伤满怀”
# Only man I ever think of #
# With regret #
“我愿将他的姓加诸我的名”
# I'd like to ahis initial #
# To my monogram #
“告诉我,牧羊人在何处? 指引迷途的羔羊?”
# Tell me where is the shepherd #
# For this lost lamb #
“我殷切地企望我的心上人”
# There's a somebody I'm longing to see #
“就是那…”
# I hope that he turns out to be #
“呵护…” （演员: 罗微娜?摩根）
“呵护我的人”
# Someone who'll watch #
# Over me #
“我是一只羔羊 迷失在树林里”
# I'm a little lamb who's lost in the wood #
“我知我可以”
# I know I could #
“永远不忘记”
# Always be good #
“那时刻关注我的...你”
# To one who'll watch #
# Over me #
“或许他不是…”
# Although he may not be the man #
“少女梦中人”
# Some girls think of as handsome #
“但我心中锁 唯他能开启”
# To my heart #
# He carries the key #
“请你告诉他,跟随我身影”
# Won't you tell him please #
# To put on some speed #
“扬鞭马奋蹄”
# Follow my lead #
“啊 我是多么需要…”
# Oh, how I need #
“一个守护...我的人”
# Someone #
# To watch #
# Over me #
[Chattering]
一些孩子开了个庆祝派对 我得去一下
Listen, uh, some of the kids are having a party, and I really should make an appearance.
你们想来吗?
Do you wanna come?
嗯…
Um, I should get Cole home.
我先带柯尔回家
好吧!我不会待太久
Okay, okay. Well, I'm not gonna be late. All right?
好的
Okay.
你没带行李
You pack light.
你有地方落脚吗?
You got a place to stay?
基督教女青年会
Y. W. C. A.
这是我以前乐队的成员 我已经跟他通过电话
That's the name of a guy that I used to play in a band with. I've already called him.
他们夫妇正等着你
He and his wife are expecting you.
我要的不是这样
This isn't the way I imagined it.
但这样是最好的办法
But it's the best way.
[Bus Approaching]
再见,罗微娜
Good-bye, Rowena.
[Exhales]
[Sighs]
我爱你
I love you.
我知道
I know.
（1980年12月8日） “今晚,约翰?列侬遇刺身亡”
[Male Newscaster] Tonight John Lennon is dead.
“警方称凶手是一狂人”
A victim of what police call "a deranged man. "
“甲壳虫乐队的灵魂人物 今晚去世,享年40岁”
[Female Newscaster] The spirit of the Beatles is dead tonight at the age of 40.
“11点钟的追思会上 一片沉寂与肃穆...”
[Male Newscaster] The mood was silence and reverence...
“当人们唱起约翰?列侬的歌时”
at the appointed hour of 11:00.
But as the crowd continued singing the Beatles' songs... the songs of John Lennon...
“现场气氛热烈、振奋、充满活力”
they became happier, vibrant, more spirited.
“或许这正是列侬一生奋斗的目的”
That was the purpose of John Lennon's music and his life.
“这是吉米?柯林斯在波特兰报导”
At O'Bryan Square in southwest Portland, this is Jim Collins reporting.
[Dog Barking]
你的眼睛怎么了?
What happened to your eye?
什么?
Sorry?
等会儿再说
Later. [Tool Clanks]
等一会儿!
In a second!
有人被...杀了
Someone was... was killed.
不,柯尔,那并不好笑
No, no, Cole. That's not funny.
约翰…
John...
列侬
Lennon.
一个音乐人
The musician.
[Sighs Deeply] You wouldn't understand.
你不会明白的
你还好吗?真令人难过
You okay? It's so sad.
[Door Slams]
柯尔,怎么回事?
[Exhales] Cole, what is it?
-他要干什么? -他有话要说
He wants to what?
He wants to tell you something. He wants to be sure you understand.
-不能以后再说吗? -现在就说!
- Couldn't we do this another time? - Now!
为什么你认为约翰?列侬的死对我无所谓? 你认为我是傻瓜?
Why do you assume that John Lennon's death would mean nothing to me?
-我知道约翰?列侬是谁  -我从没说过...
Do you think I'm stupid? I know who John Lennon is...
I never said that he...
你不对着我,我无法读你的唇语
I... I can't read your lips if you don't look at me.
我从没说过你傻
I never said that you were stupid.
如果你认为我不知道甲壳虫是谁...
You must think so...
或者根本不懂音乐,你就一定那样想过
if you think I don't know who the Beatles are or any music at all.
你以为我不关心你的事业或爱好?
You think I don't care about what it is that you do or what you love?
你是我爸爸
You're my father.
我知道音乐是什么 你可以帮助我了解更多, 但你没有
I know what music is. You could help me to know it better, but... no.
你只关心教别人  却不愿教我
You care more about teaching other people than you do about me.
- [Door Opens, Closes] - Iris.
艾莉丝
[Clears Throat]
这是什么意思?
What does this mean?
意思是"浑蛋"
That means "asshole. "
[Exhales]
该睡了
Come to bed. It's really late.
已经很晚了
我只是想要…
I was only tryin' to... [Sighs]
保护他
Protect him.
我不想伤害他…
I just didn't wanna see him hurt...
不想让他失望
or disappointed.
嗯
Hmm.
[Engine Revving]
[Revving Continues]
其次,如果曲子是有歌词的
The second, uh, would be, uh, if there are songs with words, you will need an interpreter.
- 那就需要请手语译员 现场翻译 - 就是说我们可以...
- Someone to sign the words along with the music. - Okay, so what we can...
- 有两种传递音乐的方式 - 对
- We can do two kinds of listening. - Right.
首先是纯音乐,不含歌词的
The... The first kind would be the... the pure music without words.
让学生们亲身感受音乐语言
- The music. The music. - The pure music without words...
that they could experience through putting themselves closer to the language.
灯光,或许用灯光闪烁来显示会更好
The lights. Maybe lights flashing.
（贝多芬 "降E大调第三交响曲"）
[Beethoven: "Symphony No. 3 In E flat Major"]
[Applause, Whistling]
喜欢吗?
Ah! Did you like that?
喜欢
Okay.
好
今晚压轴的曲目是列侬的歌
For our final selection tonight, we are going to do a song by John Lennon.
对席上听不到的人来说...
Now, to those of you in our audience who cannot hear...
今晚你们会感谢上帝赐你听力障碍...
this evening you will be grateful for your hearing difficulties...
因为是我来唱
because I am going to sing.
对于没有听觉障碍的观众,我郑重致歉
- [Laughing] - And to those of you...
who have no hearing problems...
my profound apologies.
[Audience Laughing]
嗯…
Um.
本人在此声明…
[Embarrassed Chuckle] On a personal note...
[Sighs]
我要把这歌献给我的儿子—柯尔
I would like to dedicate this song...
to my son...
Cole.
（约翰?列侬：“漂亮男孩”）
[Piano]
“闭上眼睛”
# Close your eyes #
“不要害怕”
# Have no fear #
“怪物已走”
# The monster's gone #
“逃得远远”
# He's on the run #
“爹地在此”
# And your daddy's here #
“漂亮,漂亮,漂亮...”
# Beautiful, beautiful, beautiful #
“漂亮的男孩”
# Beautiful boy #
“在你睡前”
# Before you go to sleep #
“向神祈祷”
# Say a little prayer #
“日日时时不断”
# Every day in every way #
“生活会变得更好”
# It's getting better and better #
“漂亮,漂亮,漂亮...”
# Beautiful, beautiful, beautiful #
“漂亮的男孩”
# Beautiful boy #
“越过重洋”
# Over the ocean #
“扬帆远航”
# Sailing away #
“我急不可待”
# I can hardly wait #
“看你长大成人”
# To see you come of age #
“但我俩都要耐心”
# But I guess we both just have to be patient #
“前路坎坷”
# 'Cause it's a long way to go #
“来日方长”
# A hard road to hoe #
“那是遥远的旅途”
# Yes, it's a long way to go #
“与此同时”
# But in the meantime #
“在你穿越马路前”
# Before you cross the street #
“请握紧我的手”
# Please take my hand #
“不断地规划 突来的机遇 构成生活的真谛”
# Life is what happens to you #
# While you're busy making other plans #
“漂亮,漂亮,漂亮...”
# Beautiful, beautiful, beautiful #
“漂亮的男孩”
# Beautiful boy #
“漂亮,漂亮,漂亮...”
# Beautiful, beautiful #
# Beautiful #
“漂亮的柯尔”
# Beautiful Cole #
（这是列侬为自己小儿子写的歌 最后一句唱出自己儿子的名字）
[Applause, Cheering, Whistling]
[Ray Charles] Well
# I got a woman #
# Way over town #
# That's good to me #
# Oh, yeah #
# Say, I got a woman #
# Way over town #
# Good to me #
# Oh, yeah #
# She give me money #
# When I'm in need #
# Yeah, she's a kind of #
# Friend indeed #
# I got a woman #
# Way over town #
# That's good to me #
# Oh, yeah #
# She saves her lovin' Early in the mornin' #
# Just for me #
# Oh, yeah #
# Oh, she's my baby #
# Oh, don't ya understand #
[Volume Increases] # Yeah, and I'm #
# Her lover man #
# I got a woman #
# Way over town #
# That's good to me #
# Oh, yeah #
# Oh, don't you know she's all right #
[De La Soul] # Mercy, ah, ah ah, ah #
1995年春季庆典 星期六下午1:00
# Ah, ah, ah #
# Ah, ah, ah Ah, ah, ah #
# Your duck may truck a man rollin' in town #
# How you do, how you do #
# I got the joint that make you jump #
# Because I'm headin' these down Tied up the merry-go- round and around #
# You know what I'm steppin' Skirts playin' with me 'cause I'm slick like that #
# I'm the greatest I've seen in the world #
[Phone Ringing]
嘿,琼,吉恩找我?
- Hey, Joan. He wants to see me? - He's with someone.
-里面有人. -那么,我稍后再来
Oh, well. I'll come back later.
霍兰先生…
Mr. Holland...
你最好还是等在这儿
you better wait.
霍兰先生,请进来
Mr. Holland, would you come in, please? [Door Closes]
-莎拉怎么了? -请坐
What's wrong with Sarah, Gene?
谢谢 我宁愿站着
- Please, sit down. - I'd rather stand, thanks.
莎拉为什么哭?
Why is Sarah crying, Gene?
好!我直说了吧
All right. I'll come right to the point.
上周二校董会的 预算会议开得十分激烈
You know how acrimonious the budget meeting was at the Board of Education meeting...
last Tuesday.
本区各校必须在九月底前 提交缩减开支10%的方案
Be that as it may...
each school in the district has been asked...
to submit proposals on ways of reducing costs by ten percent by September.
这是我的提案
This is what I've decided.
[Sighs]
[Chuckles] The entire music program.
删减所有的音乐,艺术和戏剧课
And art. And drama.
恭喜你
Well, congratulations, Gene.
30年来,你一直想法摆脱我
You've been lookin' for a way to get rid of me for 30 years...
这次终于有机会了
and they finally gave you an excuse.
我没你那么受欢迎,没有人喜欢我
You know, I'm not as popular as you. I'm not anybody's favorite anything.
那是因为你总在扮坏人，吉恩 只是你没意识到
- That's because you're the enemy, Gene. You just don't know it. - But...
我和你同样关心那些孩子
I care about these kids just as much as you do.
但如果在莫扎特,阅读,写作和算术中做选择
And if I'm forced to choose between Mozart and reading and writing and long division...
我宁可选择算术
I choose long division.
现在你能够把艺术斩草除根了，吉恩
Well, I guess you can cut the arts as much as you want, Gene.
迟早这些孩子 将再没有什么可读可写的
Sooner or later, these kids aren't gonna have anything to read or write about.
霍兰先生
Mr. Holland.
需要我帮忙吗?
If there's anything I can do.
写封推荐信?
[Laughs] A recommendation.
吉恩,我60岁了 你还能做什么?
I'm 60 years old, Gene. What are you gonna do?
你要推荐我到停尸间吗?
Write me a recommendation for the morgue?
-如果是雅各布斯，她一定会为学校力争到底  -她不会成功的
- Jacobs would've fought this. - She would've lost.
是的,她会失败 但至少争取过
Yes, she would've lost, but she would have fought this.
我也一样
And so will I!
不 不 别误会,我不是为个人职位
No. No. Do not misunderstand me.
I am not talking about my job!
而是替肯尼迪高中 曾为孩子们提供的优良教育...
I am talking about the education that students once got at Kennedy High...
与你们今天功利的举措抗辩
versus the education that you people are willing to give these kids today.
我们已反复审查多次 霍兰先生,我们已尽力了
We have been going over and over this, Mr. Holland. We've done all we can.
那就再研究一次
Then, do it again. That's what I used to tell you when you were my student, Michael...
麦可,你还是我学生时 我就这样教过你
and it served you pretty well then.
-时代不同了，霍兰先生  -我不认为时代真的相差那么大,我们做得还不够
- Well, that was a different time, Mr. Holland. - I don't think the time...
was that different; I think that more was expected of us.
还有15秒
- Fifteen seconds. - I think that the big difference is how little you people care.
我认为最大的差别 是你们关注得越来越少
- 变得越来越懒惰 - 我不喜欢你的语气,霍兰先生
- And how lazy you've become. - I resent your tone, Mr. Holland.
你不了解我们有财政困难
And I don't think you have any real appreciation for our financial problems.
得了吧!麦可!
Oh, come on, Michael!
最大问题在于你们甘于制造…
You know the big problem here is that you people are willing...
to create a generation of children who will not have the ability to think.
不会思考没有创见的一代青年
霍兰先生,时间到了
- Or create. Or listen. - [Board Official] Time, Mr. Holland.
我再说一遍,霍兰先生,我们已尽力做到最好
[Michael] Mr. Holland, as I've said, we've done the best that we can.
你们的"最好"还远不够好!
Your best is not good enough!
"有人热情洋溢的邀请我"
"A very flattering offer has been made to me to teach...
"到华盛顿一所大学教聋哑人"
at a university for the deaf in Washington, D. C.
"我还没拿定主意"
I'm not sure that I'm going to take it...
“因为我很喜欢现在学校的学生”
because I'm fond of the students in the school that I'm at now.
"我得好好考虑"
It's something to think about.
"没有女友,至少没有一个认真的"
No girlfriends yet... at least not serious ones.
"告诉爸爸,别想再要回他的车"
And tell Dad that I'm never going to give his car back.
“永远爱你们的柯尔”
Love always, Cole. "
[No Audible Dialogue]
嘿
[Bill] Hey!
Hey.
你来这里做什么?
What are you doin' here?
我有些护身内裤放在衣帽间
You know, I had some jock straps in the rinse cycle down in the locker room.
过来看看你需不需要帮忙
- Came to see if you needed any help. - Nope.
不用...
不用
No, no, no.
决定了做什么吗?
So you decided what you're gonna do yet?
重组乐队？我又太老了
Too old to start a rock band.
也许贴些小广告教钢琴课吧
Probably hang out a shingle and teach a few piano lessons.
[Exhales]
我倒喜欢退休...
- I'd love to retire. I'd... - I'm not retiring, Bill.
我不是退休,比尔 是被遗弃
I'm getting dumped.
但你没什么好担心的
[Sighs] And I don't think you have anything to worry about.
如果有砍掉足球经费的那一天
The day they cut the football budget in this state, well, now...
一定是西方文明终结之日
that will be the end of western civilization as we know it.
[Sighs] I'll tell you the truth.
跟你说句实话
[Chuckles] I'm scared to death.
(退休的生活)其实我怕得要死
大家都会想念你的
They have no idea how much they're gonna miss you around here.
- 你真的那样想? - 怎么,你怀疑? -事实上,我不信
- You really think so? - What, do you doubt it?
Well, as a matter of fact, yeah.
说来好笑,当初闹着说不干
It's almost funny. I got dragged into this gig kicking and screaming...
如今却是我唯一想做的事业
and now, it's the only thing I want to do, and...
[Sighs]
工作了一生…
You work your whole life.
教了三十年 因为相信自己可以改变什么
You work for 30 years because you think that what you do makes a difference.
相信自己对其他人有意义
You think it matters to people.
但某天早上,你醒过来发现...
Then you wake up one morning, and you find out, well, no, you've...
自己错了
you've made a little error there.
原来你是...可有可无的
You are...
expendable.
[Inhales Deeply] Oh, God.
喔!天啊!
[Chuckles] Oh, I should be laughing.
我真是好笑
你真的不需要帮忙吗?
You sure you don't need any help, huh?
好吧
All right.
[Sighs Deeply]
[Door Opens, Car Horn Honking]
[Door Closes]
[Honking Continues]
爸爸!
Dad!
你怎么来了?
What are you doing here?
学校放假了
School is out for me too.
这部老爷车,看来还不错
The old car. It looks pretty good.
这是古董车,你不能要回去
It's a classic. You can't have it back.
[Door Opens]
不!不…你不用帮我搬
No, no.
You don't have to do this.
我不想有糟老头把自己给弄伤
I don't want an old fart like you to strain yourself.
好吧 好吧,混球
Okay, okay, asshole.
你们两个闹够了没
[Sighs] That's enough, you two.
我们出去吧
Let's go out to the car. [Clears Throat]
[Piano]
那是什么声音?
Now what is that?
不清楚
Um, I don't know.
-什么?礼堂传来的声音你听不到? -我听到了,但…
What? You can't hear what's going on in the auditorium?
- Oh, yeah. I-I-I hear it, but... - Well, there's something going on in there.
好像有活动
-暑假课程吗? -不会的,还有几个星期才开课
- There isn't supposed to be... - Well, it could be a summer program.
No, the summer programs don't start for another couple of weeks.
# Louie, Louie #
# Oh, oh We gotta move now #
“标语："再见,霍兰先生!"”
[Cheering, Applause]
霍兰先生
Mr. Holland!
-史泰德勒先生? -霍兰先生,这场盛会我绝不能错过
Mr. Stadler?
I wouldn't have missed it, Mr. Holland.
你好 柯尔
Hi, Cole.
我来用手语传译
Uh, I'll sign myself.
你好…
Uh, hello. [Clears Throat]
我们大会的支持人似乎迟到了
Our master of ceremonies seems to be a little late...
所以还是我来开始吧
so I guess it's up to me to begin.
当音乐课被取消…
Um, when word first got out that the music program was cut...
和我丈夫要退休的消息传出后
and about the retirement of my husband...
我从没料到,会在这社区 引起这么大的反响
Well, I've never seen such a response from the community.
噢,看来我的表跑快了
Oh, looks like my watch is fast.
各位先生女士,请允许我介绍我们的州长
Uh, ladies and gentlemen, may I present our governor...
也是本校校友
and Kennedy High School alumnus...
尊敬的格特鲁德?蓝格女士
the most Honorable Gertrude Lang.
格特鲁德
- Gertrude. - [Chuckles] It's been a long time.
好久不见了
[Chuckles]
-谢谢你的光临. -噢…谢谢
- Thank you so much for coming. - Oh, thank you.
很抱歉,我迟到了
My... My apologies for my tardiness, and, uh, Principal Wolters...
报告华德斯校长,我有带家长证明的!
I'd like you to know... Yes, I brought a note from my mother.
[Audience Laughing]
霍兰先生对我的一生有深远影响
Mr. Holland had a profound influence on my life.
对我们许多人的一生也是一样
On a lot of lives, I know.
但我觉得,他或许会认为…  自己的大部份人生都是虚度的
And, yet, I get the feeling...
that he considers a great part of his own life misspent.
据说他一直在创作自己的交响乐
Rumor had it, he was always working on this symphony of his...
那可令他功成名就
and this was going to make him famous, rich.
Probably both.
但是霍兰先生并未发财,也未出名
But Mr. Holland isn't rich...
and he isn't famous...
小镇以外知道他的人不多
at least not outside of our little town.
他可能因此认为自己很失败
So it might be easy for him to think himself a failure.
那么他就错了
And he would be wrong...
因为他的成就远超乎名和利
because I think he's achieved a success far beyond riches and fame.
环顾四周
Look around you.
没有一个人不曾受你的影响
There is not a life in this room that you have not touched.
因为你,我们才成为了更好的人
And each one of us is a better person because of you.
霍兰先生,我们就是你的交响乐
We are your symphony, Mr. Holland.
我们就是你作品中跳跃的旋律和音符
We are the melodies and the notes of your opus.
我们是你生命的乐章
And we are the music of your life.
[Cheering, Applause]
Whoo!
霍兰先生,现在我们要回赠你一样东西
Mr. Holland, we would now like to give something back to you.
三十年来 你和师母终于等到这一场音乐会
To you and to your wife...
who, along with you, has waited 30 years for what we are about to hear.
若你愿意,可否上来…
If you will, would you please come up here and take this baton...
执起这指挥棒
指挥我们首次公演...
and lead us in the first performance ever...
of "The American Symphony" by Glenn Holland.
[Laughs]
[Music]
[Julian Lennon] # I feel #
由格伦?霍兰谱写的《美国交响曲》
# That the love around me #
# Has come #
# From another realm #
# I have lost love #
# I have found love #
# From the moment you were born #
# I could see #
# A new beginning #
# Come to me #
# Let me tell you how #
# How I've lost love #
# And how I've found love #
# In a world of broken dreams #
# I was wrong #
# To deny your feelings #
# And I'm sorry #
# If I've caused you pain #
# I was lost then #
# So confused then #
# I believe that #
# You would change that #
# There are broken hearts we can mend #
# Through the music we've learned to love again #
# Through the silence #
# Through the years #
# From the moment you were born #
# I have lost you #
# Now I've found you #
# Let me feel your heart #
# Let me hear #
# Your song #
[Shawn Stockman] # Ah #
# Little Mondays #
# Trying to embrace #
# Life with my heart #
# By all the beauty I feel and create #
# It spins and moves #
# Flows at my pace #
# Telling its story #
# From the tear running down my face #
# Visions of a sunset #
# Just appear when I close my eyes #
# Takes me closer to heaven #
# When the flute starts to fly #
# And the violin cries #
# Oh-h-h # # That's all I need #
# Whoa, whoa # # In my life #
# It's all I need and no one #
# Oh, yeah # # Can take your place by my side #
# You're all inside of me #
（这首片尾曲是本片配乐作者麦可 卡曼 为片中Cole这个角色所写的"Cole之歌" 由约翰 列侬的大儿子朱利安 列侬演唱）
# Visions of a sunset #
# Just appear when I close my eyelids #
# Takes me closer to heaven #
# When the flute starts to fly #
# And the violin cries #
# I will flee from the sorrow #
# Like the wind blows from the sky #
# Sends me closer to heaven #
# When the flute starts to fly and the violin cries #
# Oh, oh, oh #